<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scholarly and Creative Achievement or Research | Tenure and Promotion Portfolio</title>
    <link>/criterion2/</link>
      <atom:link href="/criterion2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Scholarly and Creative Achievement or Research</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Scholarly and Creative Achievement or Research</title>
      <link>/criterion2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of Educational Web Apps</title>
      <link>/criterion2/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/criterion2/software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I like to program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act of programming allows me to enter a state of flow
and I find nothing more enjoyable than whiling the hours away as I dig into a
complicated development task. Luckily I have been able to find a productive
avenue for this passion and in this section, I will highlight five different
web applications that I have had to pleasure to build. Each has not only been
incorporated in courses at Winona State, but is also open-sourced and freely
available to anyone on the web. Furthermore, they are build using modern
technology to be fast, portable, and affordable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;web-applications-for-introducing-statistical-inference&#34;&gt;Web Applications for Introducing Statistical Inference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most statistics faculty at WSU use a pedagogical approach pioneered by Drs.
Malone and Hook, where the idea of statistical evidence is introduced using
random simulations on categorical studies. Subsequently, these ideas are
formalized initially using the exact binomial test and later on in the
semester with procedures such as a t-test or chi-square test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several advantages to this approach. First, it avoids the details
of more complicated procedures like the t or chi-square tests. Also,
this approach allows the introduce core concepts of statistical inference &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;
earlier than more traditional approaches, where these ideas appear in
the final third of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there are two problems with the technologies that was
traditionally used to implement this pedagogy here at WSU and these first
three web applications were built to address these issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of my colleagues have used these applications in their courses and I
have received positive feedback from many. For example, here are comments
from Dr. Kerby (drawn from her review of my year 2019-2020 PDR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd has spent a lot of time using his programming expertise to design and
implement; two experimental design and one simulation applet. I have used the
simulation applet in my STAT 110 course, in addition to his exact binomial exact
test applet created previously, and I think they are great! It’s easy
for students to build a better understanding with no cost to them; all they
need is the internet. I find the simulation applet very easy and straight
forward for the students to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what Dr. Tisha Hooks had to say in her &lt;a href=&#34;/testimonial/hooks_letter_of_support.pdf/&#34;&gt;letter of
support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; Todd has gone above and beyond to also improve our statistics program. One
specific example I’d like to highlight is his creation of web applets that
are now used across almost all sections of introductory statistics on campus.
Before these applets were available, I required my students to purchase a
program (which cost them about $8) that was used to run simulation studies
(these simulation studies are used to intuitively introduce the idea of
statistical inference). The software was easy to use for most students, but
some did struggle and ended up falling behind early in the course. Todd
identified this added cost to the students and the issues some students had
using the program as hurdles to their learning, and he decided to do
something about it. He created a beta version of his own applet, asked us to
test it and give feedback, and then made the final version available for free
on the web. I have been using this binomial simulation study applet in my
introductory courses for about a year now, and it is fantastic. Not only is
it free, but it’s much easier for students to learn and use than the software
I used previously. In addition, he created another applet that simplifies the
computation of binomial probabilities that is now a part of several
introductory courses, as well. His applets have made my courses better, and
my students and I both owe him a great deal of gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming sections, I will highlight each web application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-binomial-simulation-app&#34;&gt;The Binomial Simulation App&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://wsu-datascience.github.io/binomial_simulation/&#34;&gt;binomial simulation
app&lt;/a&gt; was built to
replace Tinkerplots and facilitate our approach to looking for statistical
evidence through random simulations.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tinkerplots.com&#34;&gt;TinkerPlots&lt;/a&gt; program was the original
vehicle for performing simulations, but has some drawbacks. It requires
students to purchase a license through a website hosted in Australia
(students&amp;rsquo; banks occasionally decline the international purchase), has an
non-intuitive interface, and currently doesn&#39;t support the newest
versions of macOS. On top of these issues, creating simulations in
Tinkerplots is overly complicated and simulations take a VERY long time
to run.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/binomial_simulation.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. A web application built to replace TinkerPlots and facilitate introducing hypothesis testing through simulation.  This application is fast, affordable, and works on any device with a web browser.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/binomial_simulation.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; A web application built to replace TinkerPlots and facilitate introducing hypothesis testing through simulation.  This application is fast, affordable, and works on any device with a web browser.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This application was quickly adopted by a number of my colleagues over the
last few years. It is modern, running on the client-side in the user’s
browser, more intuitive, and is FAST! Students master this
application much quicker than Tinkerplots and running 1+ million trials takes
seconds; where TinkerPlots took minutes to perform 1,000 trials and would
crash if you tried many more trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allowing for a very large number of trials reduces the variability in the
simulation outcomes. I would argue that this reduces the overall cognitive
load, as there is no need to account for the variability between two
student’s results. Furthermore, a large number of trials also facilitates
talking about the law of large numbers and moving on to the exact binomial
test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-web-applications-for-the-exact-binomial-test&#34;&gt;A Web Applications for the Exact Binomial Test&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hooks-Malone approach transitions from the less-formal, more initiative
simulations to the more-formal exact binomial test. Unfortunately, the
technology used to run the exact binomial test varied from instructor to
instructor and was frankly fairly clunky. Some instructors used a spread
sheet to compute and add up individual probabilities (overly complicated in
my view) and others relied on JMP to compute a p-value (a black box with its
own quirks). I set out to create an application that would allow students to
quickly and easily complete the p-value for the exact binomial test while
still providing a bridge to understanding the connection between simulations
and this procedure.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/exact_binomial.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2: The exact binomial web application in action. Students can use this application to compute the p-value for the exact binomial test. The app is hosted for free on GitHub and has practically no limit to the number of concurrent users.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/exact_binomial.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2:&lt;/strong&gt; The exact binomial web application in action. Students can use this application to compute the p-value for the exact binomial test. The app is hosted for free on GitHub and has practically no limit to the number of concurrent users.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://wsu-datascience.github.io/exact_binomial/&#34;&gt;exact binomial web
application&lt;/a&gt;, allows
students to compute the p-value for the exact binomial test (see &lt;strong&gt;Figure
2&lt;/strong&gt;). Similar to the binomial simulation application, this app is fast,
intuitive, free, affordable to maintain, and available on any device with a
modern browser. The application is also being used by Dr. Silas Bergen (STAT 110)
and Dr. Tisha Hooks (STAT 110, STAT 210, and STAT 310).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;exact-binomial-power-app&#34;&gt;Exact Binomial Power App&lt;/h4&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/exact_binomial_power.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3: The exact binomial power application is used to introduce the concepts of type I error rate and power in STAT 310 Intermediate Statistics.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/exact_binomial_power.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3:&lt;/strong&gt; The exact binomial power application is used to introduce the concepts of type I error rate and power in STAT 310 Intermediate Statistics.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://yardsale8.github.io/exact_binomial_power/&#34;&gt;second
application&lt;/a&gt; which builds
on the exact binomial application and focuses on computing the Type I error
rate and power for an exact binomial test (see &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;). This application
is used in STAT 310 by myself and Dr. Hooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;categorical-bootstrap-app&#34;&gt;Categorical Bootstrap App&lt;/h4&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/exact_binomial_power.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 4: The categorical bootstrap web applications addresses the primary shortcoming of the StatKey CI for a Proportion app by providing a better summary of the information from the original and bootstrap samples.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/exact_binomial_power.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4:&lt;/strong&gt; The categorical bootstrap web applications addresses the primary shortcoming of the StatKey CI for a Proportion app by providing a better summary of the information from the original and bootstrap samples.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final application, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wsu-datascience.github.io/categorical_bootstrap/&#34;&gt;categorical bootstrap
app&lt;/a&gt; is the latest
addition and rounds out my suite of client-side web applications for one
sample categorial data.  This application allows students to apply &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bootstrapping_%28statistics%29&#34;&gt;the bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; to scenarios involving a single categorial sample and provides an intuitive method for introducing the concept of a confidence interval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the faculty at Winona State use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lock5stat.com/StatKey/&#34;&gt;StatKey web
apps&lt;/a&gt; as part of out class, but the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lock5stat.com/StatKey/&#34;&gt;StatKey CI for a Proportion&lt;/a&gt; app has some
shortcomings, namely the interface for entering and subsequent lack of a plot
of the data. I address these issues with this application and have
subsequently replaced the StatKey app in STAT 110.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;web-applications-for-designing-and-running-virtual-experiments&#34;&gt;Web Applications for Designing and Running Virtual Experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STAT 321 Industrial Design of Experiments is a course focused on teaching
students to design, implement, and analyze experiments. My colleagues have
designed a suite of &amp;ldquo;laboratory&amp;rdquo; experiments intended to provide students
with hands-on experience implementing and running an experiment from
start to finish. These labs are a standard part of my design for face-to-face
sections of STAT 321, but the response to Covid-19 threw a wrench in my
original plans last spring semester. It is hard to fire catapults or drop
helicopters virtually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To replicate the experience of designing and running experiments virtually, I
have developed two web apps that simulate an ultrasonic welding experiment
(linked below). &lt;a href=&#34;https://medcraveonline.com/MSEIJ/modeling-and-prediction-of-weld-strength-in-ultrasonic-metal-welding-process-using-artificial-neural-network-and-multiple-regression-method.html&#34;&gt;Anand et al.
(2018)&lt;/a&gt;,
conducted an ultrasonic welding experiment and then fit a multivariate
regression model to the results. My web application is based on their regression model and
provide a random, repeatable simulation of this process. An important feature of
this model is there is a nice local maximum inside the design space,
allowing for the application of response surface designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;two-simulated-experiment-web-applications&#34;&gt;Two Simulated Experiment Web Applications&lt;/h4&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/welding_experiments.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 7. Two web applications that allow students to design and run a simulated ultrasonic welding experiment. The left-hand application facilitates both full and fractional factorial designs. The right-hand application adds four operators to allow for blocking.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/welding_experiments.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 7.&lt;/strong&gt; Two web applications that allow students to design and run a simulated ultrasonic welding experiment. The left-hand application facilitates both full and fractional factorial designs. The right-hand application adds four operators to allow for blocking.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two applications are illustrated in &lt;strong&gt;Figure 8&lt;/strong&gt;, where &lt;a href=&#34;https://wsu-datascience.github.io/weld_strength_experiment/&#34;&gt;left-hand
application&lt;/a&gt;
facilitates a full or fractional factorial design, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://wsu-datascience.github.io/welding_strength_blocking/&#34;&gt;right-hand
application&lt;/a&gt;
adds an imaginary operator to allow for blocked designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have several additions that I would like to make to these applications.
First, I would like to improve the underlying model, perhaps by using some of
the other models found in the literature. Second, I would like to add the
option to perform trials at center or radial points, which would facilitate a
broader range of designs. There are also tentative plans to add additional
factors, covariates, temporal effects, and/or other information (like cost
and time) to allow for wider application. Finally, I also plan to abstract my
current code to allow turn this site into a framework that can be applied to
another scenario without much of a hassle. This would allow me to build an
entire suite of virtual experiments that are open source and can be shared
with the statistics education community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section, evidence was provided of substantial contributions in the
area of technologically delivered academic products (See Appendix G of the
Master Agreement) in the form of six web applications that are used my
colleagues, as well as my own, courses. Each web app is modern, fast, and
easy to use; and all are freely available on the web on any device with a
modern browser.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at Professional Meetings</title>
      <link>/criterion2/presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/criterion2/presentations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many areas of data science require strong programming skills and I have given
several presentations in recent years on two topics: introducing software
development best practices into data science curriculum and talking data
management algorithms starting with data verbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching-data-science-students-to-write-clean-code&#34;&gt;Teaching Data Science Students to Write Clean Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For close to 10 years, I have had the opportunity to teach students
programming on one level or another; be it introductory/advanced CS or
various DSCI courses. One worry that I have had (and I suspect I share with
other STAT/DSCI instructors) is how to go about evaluating and improving
students’ code. This year, I have spent some time learning what the experts,
namely experienced software engineers, had to say about clean code. In this
section I will discuss two presentations that shared what I have learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;evaluating-name-southern-mn-stat-chat-at-st-olaf-college-april-26-2019&#34;&gt;Evaluating Name, Southern MN Stat Chat at St. Olaf College, April 26, 2019&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/names.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. I shared what I have learned about evaluating the quality of variable and function names at the Southern MN Stat Chat.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/names.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; I shared what I have learned about evaluating the quality of variable and function names at the Southern MN Stat Chat.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first talk on clean code focused on evaluating the quality of variable and
function names in code and was presented at the Southern MN Stat Chat at St.
Olaf College, April 26, 2019. This talk has become a regular feature in my
DSCI 330 course and parts of this material were incorporated into the next
talk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;teaching-data-science-students-to-write-clean-code-sdss-2019-belleview-wa&#34;&gt;Teaching Data Science Students to Write Clean Code, SDSS 2019, Belleview, WA.&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/clean.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2. The clean code talk tells the story of Doug, a budding data scientist intent on cleaning up his code, earning an A, and thwarting his nemesis&amp;ndash;the mean Dr. Iverson.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/clean.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; The clean code talk tells the story of Doug, a budding data scientist intent on cleaning up his code, earning an A, and thwarting his nemesis&amp;ndash;the mean Dr. Iverson.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second extended talk on teaching students to write clean code was presented
at the 2019 Symposium on Data Science &amp;amp; Statistics (SDSS 2019) in Belleview,
WA. This talk built on the last, but also illustrated the importance of
teaching students to refactor code and run unit tests. The talk had a unique
format, presenting the material by telling the story of a fictitious data
science student intent on getting an A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kelly McConville, Associate Professor of Statistics at Reed College and
program chair of the SDSS 2019, attended the talk and I asked her for comments.
Here is what she had to say in her &lt;a href=&#34;/testimonial/mcconville_letter_of_support.pdf&#34;&gt;letter of
support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can safely say that of all of the talks at the conference, Dr. Iverson&#39;s
talk had the most direct impact on my teaching. I am currently teaching a
data science course and added several of Dr. Iverson&#39;s suggestions into both
my teaching and assessment materials. (His talk is also helping me to write
better code.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also like to address Dr. Iverson&#39;s presentation skills as I felt that
he gave the audience a good understanding of him as a teacher. Dr. Iverson
has a fun, playful, and rather self-deprecating presentation persona. I can
see this persona making him very accessible to his students. He taught the
audience about writing clean code (a rather dry topic usually) through a fun
fictional story about a student assignment where the student is the hero and
the professor (Dr. Iverson) is the villain. His student iterates through
refactoring their code, going for rather messy code to nice, clean code.
Throughout the iterations, Dr. Iverson gives us concrete suggestions of ways
code should be refactored and clearly explains why these are good practices.
He used pictures, highlighted code chunks, and even stick figures to help
tell the story in a clean and engaging way. He reinforced the key takeaway
messages throughout the talk and provided us with useful additional resources
at the end. I was wildly impressed with the amount of effectively covered
content in his talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I will discuss two presentations, a poster and a talk, on teaching data
management with data verbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-management-with-data-verbs&#34;&gt;Data Management with Data Verbs&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/verbs.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3. Dr. Chris Malone and I submitted an extended abstract (pictured in part here) that was peer-reviewed and accepted as a talk for SDSS 2020.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/verbs.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Chris Malone and I submitted an extended abstract (pictured in part here) that was peer-reviewed and accepted as a talk for SDSS 2020.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two years, I have been collaborating with Dr. Chris Malone on
implementing a new data science curriculum focused on data verbs. We
presented our initial work in a poster at SDSS 2019 (Dr. Malone was the
primary author) and our extended abstract on this topic was accepted as &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/sdss/2020/onlineprogram/Program.cfm&#34;&gt;a
talk for SDSS 2020&lt;/a&gt; (I
was the primary author and presenter&amp;ndash;see &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;). I discuss each presentation below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-data-verbs-to-teach-the-management-of-tabular-data-sdss-2019-belleview-wa&#34;&gt;Using Data Verbs to Teach the Management of Tabular Data, SDSS 2019, Belleview, WA.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Chris Malone (primary author) and I presented on our approach to teaching
data verbs in a software/technology agnostic fashion at SDSS 2019. This is
material that has grown out of our DSCI 210 introductory data science course,
but we think will also influence other areas of the curriculum such as DSCI
325 The Management of Structured Data and DSCI 430 Data Science at Scale. I
gave a follow-up talk on our efforts the following year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-management-with-data-verbs-sdss-2020-virtual&#34;&gt;Data Management with Data Verbs, SDSS 2020, Virtual.&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/verbs_talk.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 4. My SDSS 2020 talk shared many of the ideas and activities on teaching data management with data verbs developed in collaboration with Dr. Chris Malone .&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/verbs_talk.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.&lt;/strong&gt; My SDSS 2020 talk shared many of the ideas and activities on teaching data management with data verbs developed in collaboration with Dr. Chris Malone .
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk presented our updated approach and encouraged the audience to teach
data management in a software-agnostic style (discussed in more detail in the
section on &lt;a href=&#34;/criterion1/curriculum_design/&#34;&gt;curriculum development&lt;/a&gt;. The talk incorporates our previous
activities for teaching data management with data verbs, as well as new
material on teaching the management of unstructured data through data
origami.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communicating our work with a wider audience is an important part of academic
work, and in this section, you have seen evidence of effective dissemination
of new approaches to data science curriculum at both local and national meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop Development and Delivery</title>
      <link>/criterion2/workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/criterion2/workshops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last four years, I have created and executed four pre-conference
workshops in collaboration with my WSU colleagues. These activities fall under
the category of growth of peers and other scholars (See Appendix G of the
Master Agreement) and constitute a major part of my scholarly and creative
output since joining the Department of Mathematics and Statistics in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will start with a discussion of the USCOTS 2019 pre-conference workshop
decimating the WSU core data science curriculum that was presented by all six
data science faculty. I took the leadership role in conceptualizing,
proposing, and organizing the program for the workshop and there is evidence
of a resounding success. I see this workshop as the crowning jewel in this
area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section is rounded out with a discussion of a sequence of three workshops
on data visualization that I planned and executed with my colleague Dr. Silas
Bergen. The opportunity to present three workshops on similar content allowed
us the opportunity to hone the content and delivery, and resulting in a
polished and successful workshop at SDSS 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of this section, you will see ample evidence of meaningful
contribution to the scholarly growth of peers and other scholars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-core-curriculum-for-undergraduate-data-science-uscots-2019-college-station-pa&#34;&gt;A Core Curriculum for Undergraduate Data Science, USCOTS 2019, College Station, PA&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/uscots19_core_banner.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. The entire WSU data science faculty presented our core data science curriculum in a 2-day pre-conference workshop at USCOTS 2019. On top of being in charge of the original proposal and the subsequent organization and division of labor, I also contributed to half of the design and implementation of sessions .&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/uscots19_core_banner.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; The entire WSU data science faculty presented our core data science curriculum in a 2-day pre-conference workshop at USCOTS 2019. On top of being in charge of the original proposal and the subsequent organization and division of labor, I also contributed to half of the design and implementation of sessions .
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years, the data science faculty at WSU have been expressing a desire to
share our DSCI curriculum with a larger audience. In January of 2018, five of
these faculty attended a workshop on data science curriculum. Our takeaway
was we have a head start on the conceptualization and development of data
science curriculum and should find a venue to share what we have learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on our many discussions on this topic, I submitted a proposal for a
16-hour pre-conference workshop at USCOTS 2019 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1VBNfOcqOWcI8C5cVFfuV9Jy7s2FajHGcrCiRgzX0hck/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;available
here&lt;/a&gt;)
that was ultimately accepted. The resulting workshop consisted of 4 four-hour
sessions, one dedicated to each of the following topics: the introductory
course, data visualization, the management of data, and statistical learning
theory. We believe that these four topics should form the core of any
data science curriculum and hoped to convince the audience that all programs
should include courses on each.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/uscots19_core_block_1_and_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2. The two blocks that I help create and present scored high in terms of overall quality, presentation, and the quality of the break-out activities.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/uscots19_core_block_1_and_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; The two blocks that I help create and present scored high in terms of overall quality, presentation, and the quality of the break-out activities.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I create and present two of the four blocks, collaborating with Dr. Chris
Malone to the first block (The Intro Class) and Drs. Hooks and Kerby on the
third (Data Management). As shown in &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;, both of these sections
score high in overall format, presentation, and the quality of break-out
activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to highlight our success on two additional goals by focusing on some responses to the questions &lt;em&gt;What were the most valuable aspects of the workshop?&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt; ) and &lt;em&gt;If you were to implement one thing from the workshop, what would that be?&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;Implement&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we wanted to make it clear that data science was a science
in its own right and it is not sufficient to simply bundle up existing data science and statistic courses. The following comments suggest that we hit the mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;For me, the most valuable aspect was to learned what is data science and how to teach it. As a statistician I never thought about the cleaning and manipulation of data, only when necessary. So it is interesting to see part of a course dedicated to this&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;breaking several myths and pre-conceived notion I have about data science being a statistician&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;All aspects of the workshops are very valuable. The understanding that DS should not be just a combination of stats courses and CS courses is new to me, and a great advice.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;The most important takeaway I got from this workshop is the philosophy of teaching data science&amp;ndash;the fact that it is distinct from statistics and the importance of understanding data science ideas apart from a particular programming language. I hope to help my school build a DS program that is more than a repackaging of existing math/stat/comp. science courses.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we think that it is important to develop curriculum &lt;em&gt;software or
technology agnostic&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of teaching a specific technology, you should
instead teach core concepts, and then translate them to various platforms.
The following comments suggest we were also successful getting this idea
across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Loved the software agnostic activities and want to incorporate that more into our courses!&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The very &amp;ldquo;hands-on&amp;rdquo; activities that emphasized software-agnostic learning of data science concepts.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;I LOVED the on-paper data wrangling exercises. And just learning more about the overall structure of your program was helpful; you&#39;d obviously thought a lot about what skills were important, etc.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement:&lt;/strong&gt;&#39;&lt;em&gt;I am definitely going to add more non-programming data wrangling to our stats course that teaches dplyr. It will be a useful first step that we are currently missing.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Software agnostic activities&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/uscots19_core_overall.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3. Participants were very satisfied with the workshop overall.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/uscots19_core_overall.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; Participants were very satisfied with the workshop overall.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we hoped that we could put together a workshop that provides value
and insight on the creation of a data science program. Responses to the
participant survey, in particular the participant ratings on the overall workshop shown
in &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt; and the comments highlighted above suggest that we were very
successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-visualization-workshops&#34;&gt;Data Visualization Workshops&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I will discuss a series of three workshops that I developed in
collaboration with Dr. Bergen. The final result was an invitation to present
a pre-conference workshop presented at SDSS 2019 that was a resounding
success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;web-scraping-and-data-visualization-with-python-ad-tableau-uscots-2017&#34;&gt;Web Scraping and Data Visualization with Python ad Tableau. USCOTS 2017&lt;/h4&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/uscots17_banner.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 4. Dr. Bergen and I ran a USCOTS workshop that took participants through the entire data cycle.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/uscots17_banner.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Bergen and I ran a USCOTS workshop that took participants through the entire data cycle.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2017, Dr. Silas and I ran a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.causeweb.org/cause/uscots/uscots17/workshop/2&#34;&gt;USCOTS pre-conference
workshop&lt;/a&gt; that
took the participants through the entire data cycle. In the first half of the
workshop (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WSU-DataScience/USCOTS2017_workshop&#34;&gt;material available
here&lt;/a&gt;) I taught the
participants focused on teaching the basics of the Python programming
language, followed by the basics of web scraping. After the participants had a
handle on basic Python tools, they were introduced to scraping the web using
the Beautiful Soup module. Then, they learned the basic theory around
visualization, which was subsequently applied to the data from the Current
using Tableau.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/uscots17.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 5. Almost all participants found my portion of the workshop useful.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/uscots17.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5.&lt;/strong&gt; Almost all participants found my portion of the workshop useful.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My portion of the workshop was well-received. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt; illustrates that
almost all participants were satisfied. I would also like to share a note
regarding the workshop that one happy participant sent to Dr. Nicole
Williams, Chair of the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Professor &amp;amp; Department Chair Williams,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sending to a quick note to compliment your department and
university for hiring Dr. Silas Bergen and Dr. Todd Iverson.  It
is *not *a routine practice of mine to take the time to contact
the leadership of workshop presenters.  But, in this case, I wanted to
do so.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was deeply impressed by the 2-day workshop on Web Scraping &amp;amp; Data
Visualization that Drs. Bergen &amp;amp; Iverson provided last week at the
U.S. Conference on Teaching Statistics (USCOTS).  It was clear that
both of them have developed not only the content knowledge, but that
they also continue to hone their pedagogical knowledge for
facilitating the knowledge and skills of their learners in the
emerging field of data science.  From what I was able to discern, they
had a tall order to fill because there was much variation in the prior
knowledge and skills of those of us who enrolled in the workshop.  I,
for one, was completely new to the software they used (Python and
Tableau) while others appeared to know one or the other, or a similar
type of program making the transfer more easily.  Still, what was
particularly noteworthy about both Silas and Todd, was their
attentiveness to my struggles.  Rather than dismiss me as one who
would not &amp;ldquo;get it,&amp;rdquo; they each took the time to sit near me, while the
other was presenting, and offer countless help, as needed. And, while
doing that, they also showed awareness of the other learners and
addressed their needs, too.  Their patience and kindness were much
appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am not seeing myself as a future &amp;ldquo;web scraper,&amp;rdquo; I felt that
the exposure I received from Todd will be very helpful to me as I now
better understand the process others go through, including the
potential for errors, when creating more manageable &amp;ldquo;big data&amp;rdquo; sets.
 The exposure to data visualization was quite intriguing and set the
stage for the conference&#39;s opening talk (which highly reflected ideas
Silas covered) and other sessions I attended where additional software
(besides Tableau) was introduced.  I appreciate how Silas took the
time to first cover the Elementary Perceptual Task (EPT) principles
that underlie quality visualizations before working with Tableau.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is turning into more than a quick note, so I will conclude here.
 In sum, it is my impression that your department and university are
fortunate to have Dr. Bergen and Dr. Iverson.  Undoubtedly, they will
continue to grow professionally and benefit not only their students,
but faculty colleagues, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rachelle Kisst Hackett&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also several positive
comments (see comments 1 and 2 below), but there was still some room for
improvement. You can access the entire &lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/qxmm0k&#34;&gt;participant
survey here&lt;/a&gt;, but I would like to share four comments, two
positive and two on suggested improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Finally learning Python and seeing how to implement it in a data science context!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The mini-tasks in both the Python and Tableau portions were incredibly useful to learn as we went.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I felt the Python portion was a little fast-paced, but I was able to catch up on the breaks.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“&lt;em&gt;A lot of material to cover in the time allotted. It could be longer or the two topics could even be split into two workshops&lt;/em&gt;,”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last comment, in particular, rang true and we have taken this feedback to heart
in subsequent workshops by shifting the entire focus to data visualization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;data-visualization-theory-and-pedagogy-icots-2018-kyoto-japan&#34;&gt;Data Visualization Theory and Pedagogy, ICOTS 2018, Kyoto, Japan&lt;/h4&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/icots18_banner.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 6. Dr. Bergen and I ran an ICOTS workshop focusing on data visualization theory and pedagogy.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/icots18_banner.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 6.&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Bergen and I ran an ICOTS workshop focusing on data visualization theory and pedagogy.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July of 2018, Dr. Silas Bergen and I presented a workshop on the
foundation of data visualization theory and pedagogy at &lt;a href=&#34;http://icots.info/10/?workshop=E&#34;&gt;ICOTS
2018&lt;/a&gt; in Kyoto, Japan. In contrast to our
first workshop, which blended two separate topics over four 4-hour blocks,
this time we devoted our time exclusively to data visualization. We focused
on three components of visualization: the grammar of graphics, the elementary
perceptional task, and graphic design gestalt principles throughout
four 1-hour sessions. While we had a very low response rate, the results of a
participant survey are available here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/e3IGkD&#34;&gt;Participant
Survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/icots18_block2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 7. I developed and ran the second block of the workshop, which compare introduced visualization in Altair (Python) in hopes of reinforcing the concepts of the grammar of graphics introduced in the first block.  This portion of the workshop was not as well-received as I would like, but I was improved the following year (see Figure 9)&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/icots18_block2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 7.&lt;/strong&gt; I developed and ran the second block of the workshop, which compare introduced visualization in Altair (Python) in hopes of reinforcing the concepts of the grammar of graphics introduced in the first block.  This portion of the workshop was not as well-received as I would like, but I was improved the following year (see &lt;strong&gt;Figure 9&lt;/strong&gt;)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in charge of the second block, which was designed to reinforce the
concepts from the grammar of graphics by constructing visualizations using
the Altair in Python. Unfortunately, this part of the workshop was not as
well-received as I would like. The pacing of this block was off,
resulting in spending too much time &amp;ldquo;in the weeds&amp;rdquo; and not enough looking at interesting visualizations.  The effect of this mismanagement of time can be seen in the participant responses in &lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt; as well as the comments provided below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;I wasn&#39;t particularly interested in learning Python, so have less opinion about that. I wasn&#39;t quite sure how the Python portion and Tableau portion fit together&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A little less detail on inner workings of Python, so we would have time to get more interesting graphs.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I was able to address these issues in a workshop the following summer (see below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;data-visualization-theory-and-pedagogy-sdss-2019-belleview-wa&#34;&gt;Data Visualization Theory and Pedagogy, SDSS 2019, Belleview, WA&lt;/h4&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/sdss19_banner.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 8. Dr. Bergen and I were invited to run a workshop on data visualization at SDSS 2019.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/sdss19_banner.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 8.&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Bergen and I were invited to run a workshop on data visualization at SDSS 2019.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bergen and I were invited to present our workshop on data visualization
at a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/sdss/2019/onlineprogram/Program.cfm&#34;&gt;pre-conference workshop for SDSS
2019&lt;/a&gt;.
This was our second time presenting this workshop (see above), and we made a
number of improvements.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/sdss19_block2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 9. Again, I in charge of the second block of the workshop, but this time we compared the code for visualization in Altair (Python) and ggplot (R) to reinforce the concepts of the grammar of graphics introduced in the first block.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/sdss19_block2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 9.&lt;/strong&gt; Again, I in charge of the second block of the workshop, but this time we compared the code for visualization in Altair (Python) and ggplot (R) to reinforce the concepts of the grammar of graphics introduced in the first block.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on participant feedback from the last workshop, I made several changes
to the second block of the workshop. Instead of getting bogged down in the details of Python and Altair, participants compared the code for visualizations constructed with the Altair in Python and ggplot in R. This was a more successful approach (compare &lt;strong&gt;Figures 7 &amp;amp; 9&lt;/strong&gt;).  Full results of the participant survey are &lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/zcaZSK&#34;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt; and I have provided a number of positive responses below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Select responses to &amp;ldquo;What were the most valuable aspects of the workshop?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip; I also really liked learning how to use ggplot in Python, altair, and Tableau. I felt like the examples and activities used in the teaching sessions were well structured and I took away some good tips to use in my teaching.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Hands on application of grammar of graphics theory in ggplot and altair.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Showing altair and ggplot side-by-side was very useful, as were the exercises and lastly seeing the capabilities of Tableau.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip; I also really liked learning how to use ggplot in Python, altair, and Tableau. I felt like the examples and activities used in the teaching sessions were well structured and I took away some good tips to use in my teaching.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip; The side by side of ggplot2, which I know very well, and Altair, which I know nothing about, is great.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Hands on application of grammar of graphics theory in ggplot and altair.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this section, evidence was provided of a successful, well-received
series of workshop that provided an avenue to decimate the data science
curriculum developed at WSU and contributed to the growth of my fellow data
science educators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
