<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Service to the university and community | Tenure and Promotion Portfolio</title>
    <link>yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/</link>
      <atom:link href="yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Service to the university and community</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/yardsale8.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Service to the university and community</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Service to the Statistics and Data Science Education Communities</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/community/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;First, I would like to highlight three contributions to the mathematics,
statistics, and data science education community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uscots-2021-planning-committee&#34;&gt;USCOTS 2021 Planning Committee&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/uscots.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1: I am on the planning committee for USCOTS 2021, organizing and evaluating the workshop proposals.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/uscots.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: I am on the planning committee for USCOTS 2021, organizing and evaluating the workshop proposals.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed in a &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/criterion2/workshops/&#34;&gt;section on criterion 2&lt;/a&gt;, I have conducted several workshops on
teaching data science, two of which were conducted at the United States
Conference on Teaching Statistics (USCOTS). This year, likely due to these
workshops, I was asked to serve on the planning committee for USCOTS
2021&amp;ndash;co-chairing the planning of the pre-conference workshop. Planning this
year&#39;s conference has been a challenge&amp;ndash;it is being run virtually&amp;ndash;and I am
excited to serve in this capacity for a conference that has had a big impact
on my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-visualization-in-python-sdss-2019-belleview-wa&#34;&gt;Data Visualization in Python, SDSS 2019, Belleview, WA&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/invited.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1: I organized and chaired an invited session for SDSS 2019 that brought in experts to teach the audience about data visualizations in Python.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/invited.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: I organized and chaired an invited session for SDSS 2019 that brought in experts to teach the audience about data visualizations in Python.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the request of Dr. Silas Bergen, I organized an invited session for the
2019 Symposium on Data Science &amp;amp; Statistics (SDSS 2019) that focuses on
inducing the audience to data visualization in Python. The first speaker,
Stephen Elston from Quantia Analytic, introduced the audience to the
MatPlotLib and the Seaborn libraries. This talk was designed to provide easy
access to standard statistical visualizations. The second and third talks
focus on Altair, which provides a visualization framework that (a) is based
on the Grammar of Graphics, (b) allows visualization to be hosted on at sites
such as GitHub and (b) is built on the Vega and Vega-Lite frameworks. These
talks were presented by Dominik Moritz from the University of Washington
and Kanit &amp;ldquo;Ham&amp;rdquo; Wongsuphasawat from Apple; two contributors to both Vega and
Altair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-course-on-teaching-data-science-project-next-2020&#34;&gt;A Course on Teaching Data Science, Project Next, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/project_next.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2: Chris Malone and I developed and taught a Project NExT short course on teaching data science.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/project_next.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Chris Malone and I developed and taught a Project NExT short course on teaching data science.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after earning a Ph.D., I was able to participate in Project NExT, a
professional development program for new/recent Ph.D.s. This program had a
big impact on my career and this year I had the opportunity to give back. Dr.
Chris Malone and I taught a short course on teaching data science described
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curriculum for an introductory data science course varies tremendously as
the definition of data science depends on one’s perspective. This workshop
will discuss how the curriculum for our introductory data science course has
changed so that students who have a diverse background in computing can
succeed. Best practices, including specific examples, for the teaching of an
introductory data science course will be presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Service to Winona State</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/university/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/criterion5/university/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the area of service to the University, I have served on several
departmental and university faculty committees, most recently taking on the
role of co-chair of CPPS. In this section, I will highlight three specific
areas of service and then give an overview of other activities related to
this criterion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;co-chairing-course-and-program-proposal-subcommittee-cpps&#34;&gt;Co-chairing Course and Program Proposal Subcommittee (CPPS)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I am serving as co-chair of the Course Program Proposal
Subcommittee (CPPS). This semester the committee has proceeded with its
regular business, approving the proposals for 7 new courses, 3 revised
courses, and 9 program revisions. In the meantime, I have been working with
Curriculog Work Group on improving the process of proposing changes to courses
and programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;implement-the-prediction-accuracy-portion-of-mudac-2017&#34;&gt;Implement the Prediction Accuracy Portion of MUDAC 2017&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/kaggle.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1: In 2017 and 2018, I organized the data analytics portion of the MUDAC competition, where Kaggle was used validate the models and to track the leaderboard in real-time.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/img/kaggle.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: In 2017 and 2018, I organized the data analytics portion of the MUDAC competition, where Kaggle was used validate the models and to track the leaderboard in real-time.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for the 2017 MUDAC competition, the statistics and data
science faculty decided to include a new component in the competition.
The general sentiment was that, in past years, a team’s presentation skills were
weighted too heavily and teams that had more advanced analytics skills did
not get the recognition we believed they deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To facilitate this new part of the competition, I took on the responsibility
for the implementation and operation of two competitions using Kaggle. First,
a preliminary completion was constructed using a well-known data set to allow
participants to become familiar with the Kaggle framework. Teams were given a
week to play around with these data and asked to make at least one successful
submission before the start of the competition. The results of this
preliminary competition had no impact on the actual competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Kaggle competition was used to evaluate each team’s
performance for the actual prediction problem. Throughout the
competition, teams made submissions to the site and were able to track
their (approximate) performance on a public leaderboard. The final
results of the competition were determined by a private leaderboard that
was made available after the competition closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analytics portion of the competition was very successful and the MUDAC competition
has been using this framework ever since (at least until the pandemic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-the-program-objectives-for-the-data-science-program&#34;&gt;Update the Program Objectives for the Data Science Program&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my prior experience with program assessment, I was excited to
contribute to the program assessment of the statistics and data
science programs. We took the first step in this direction this year by
formalizing the program outcomes for the data science program. Dr. Chris
Malone and I met several times to consider these outcomes, using
recommendations made from various sources and attempted to align
the topics and sections to those found in the ASA recommendations for a
statistics major. This initial draft was the basis for the program
outcomes that were approved by the subgroup and department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-overview-of-other-service-activities&#34;&gt;An Overview of Other Service Activities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the items above represent the most substantial work in this area, here
is a list of other activities in the area of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last four years, I have served on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Statistics Subcommittee each year, taking a leadership role in
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revising the internship application and assessment materials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revising the oral and written communication courses in both the statistics and data science majors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporting a 5-year program review for both the data science and statistics programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helped revamp the general education assessment materials for STAT 110.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Served on the planning committee for MUDAC 2017 and MUDAC 2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the CPPS committee as a regular member for one year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;three search committees, one for a tenure-track position and the others for fixed-term positions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the SLAC subcommittee for two years, helping organize departmental seminars and outside speakers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the General Education Program and Policies (GEPS) committee for one semester.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the WSU FA Technology and Online Education Committees one year each.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
