<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Evidence of Continuing Preparation and Study | Tenure and Promotion Portfolio</title>
    <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/</link>
      <atom:link href="yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Evidence of Continuing Preparation and Study</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/yardsale8.github.io/tenure/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Evidence of Continuing Preparation and Study</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Participating in Continuing Education Courses</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/continuing_education/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/continuing_education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, I have completed six of online
courses (participating continuing education courses and/or formal
education/study&amp;ndash;Appendix G of Master Agreement). These courses cover a
wide breadth of topics, including functional programming, distributed computing,
building client-server applications, and finally a course on developing
online and blended courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of this section, you will see evidence of a substantial and formal
course of study, which is had an impact on developing and updating curriculum
in data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;completion-of-online-courses-in-data-science&#34;&gt;Completion of Online Courses in Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first four courses are were completed to prepare for the development of
three new data science elective, a special topics course on functional
distributed programming in the spring semester of 2017 and two new elective
approved and implemented in 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;complete-a-coursera-course-on-the-hadoop-platform&#34;&gt;Complete a Coursera Course on the Hadoop Platform&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://hadoop.apache.org&#34;&gt;Hadoop framework&lt;/a&gt; supports distributing the
storage and processing of very large quantities of data across many machines
and is used by &lt;a href=&#34;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/HADOOP2/PoweredBy&#34;&gt;many social media and tech
companies&lt;/a&gt;
such as eBay, Facebook, and Twitter. In preparation for teaching a special
topics course in the spring of 2017, I completed a Coursera course on the
Hadoop framework during the 2016 fall term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curriculum for this course included an overview of the basic components
of the Hadoop framework, as well as the basics of writing MapReduce and Spark
applications. Completing this course was a positive experience that directly
impacted the curriculum in STAT 489 and inspired the associated textbook.
This course also led me to learning the Spark SQL framework, which is
featured in the DSCI 430 course developed the following year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The certificate for completion of this course can be seen by navigating
this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/QRTQKUPSZDRY&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;two-courses-on-functional-programming-in-scala&#34;&gt;Two Courses on Functional Programming in Scala&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In anticipation of designing and implementing DSCI 430 Data Science at Scale,
I completed 2 Coursera courses during the 2017 summer break. The first
introduced functional programing in the Scala programming language and the
second built on the first by teaching functional design principles in Scala.
Spark, the primary focus of DSCI 430, is written in Scala and while this
course uses the Python bindings to Spark, it was still beneficial to learn
about the under-pinnings of the framework. Below you will find the
certificates for the completion of each course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/FJSWZZK7DMF7&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functional Programming Principles in
Scala&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/JY34BG86VHC5&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functional Program Design in
Scala&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;cleaning-data-in-python&#34;&gt;Cleaning Data in Python&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the topics in covered in DSCI 430 Data Science at Scale is the process
of cleaning data. To make sure that my understandings of cleaning data in
Python was up-to-date, I complete a &lt;a href=&#34;www.datacamp.com&#34;&gt;DataCamp&lt;/a&gt; course on
this subject. The completion of this course helped me formalize a
step-by-step process for cleaning data, as well as introduced me to some
effective techniques for online courses. The certificate of completion is
&lt;a href=&#34;testimonial/data_camp_data_cleaning.pdf&#34;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;elixirdeveloping-with-elixirotp&#34;&gt;Elixir—Developing with Elixir/OTP&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to building client-side educational application, like those
highlighted under &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion2/software/&#34;&gt;criterion 2&lt;/a&gt;. While
the Elm programming language is great for creating responsive modern
client-side applications, it requires an interface with another language when
creating client-server applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 2019 fall semester, I started to gain the requisite knowledge to
build a server-side client by completing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pragmaticstudio.com/courses/elixir&#34;&gt;Pragmatic Studio course on
Elixir&lt;/a&gt;. Elixir is a language
that is built on top of Erlang and is tailor-built for the sorts of tasks
completed by a server-side client. In particular, I really liked the actor
model that was employed and streamlined by Elixir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of completing a course like this one is seeing the
author’s pedological approach to online learning. In this case, the
couple that creates the videos perform the lectures in tandem and switch
off presenting topics; timing the transitions when a topic changes or
when making a counterpoint. They also had good transitions between
showing them talking to the camera and them talking over a computer
screen or terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;complete-the-weteach-courses-on-teaching-online-and-blended-courses&#34;&gt;Complete the WeTeach Courses on Teaching Online and Blended Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last summer, over the last four summers, I had the opportunity to teach
STAT 110 in the online format. Then COVID happened. While I had sat in on the
WeTeach course in my first year at WSU, I thought it was to time revisit (and
actually complete) this course. This summer, I re-enrolled and completed in
the WeTeach course offered by Minnesota State, which focus on the best
practices for teaching online and blended courses. I have fully completed the
course (see the &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/testimonial/WeTeachCertificate.pdf&#34;&gt;attached certificate&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my takeaways from retaking this course was just how much the first
time through has impacted my course development. WeTeach encourages extra
organization and communication with students and I am happy to say that my
online courses meet these goals. In the flip side, taking the course
reinforced that I can improve my courses by building better rubrics for
improving the communication of my expectations and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the goals of the WeTeach courses is to introduce the requirements for
certifying a course under Quality Matters and encourage faculty to apply for
this certification. I am in the process of setting up STAT 110 to meet the
expectations, and also plan to submit the DSCI 611 course that I am creating
for HLA for certification.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structured Study to Improve Courses and Tools</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/other_structured_study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/other_structured_study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/continuing_education/&#34;&gt;formal online coursework&lt;/a&gt; discussed in a different section, I will also
provide evidence of self-guided structured study in two other areas: learning
to build client-side web applications using the Elm programming language and
a program of study on the management of unstructured data with Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her letter of support, Mariah Quam&amp;ndash;a data science alum&amp;ndash;described my willingness to learn and present the nex&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-to-write-web-applications-in-elm&#34;&gt;Learning to Write Web Applications in Elm&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/elm.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. To facilitate the creation educational web application like the binomial simulation app, I completed a course of self-study to learn the Elm programming language.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/elm.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; To facilitate the creation educational web application like the binomial simulation app, I completed a course of self-study to learn the Elm programming language.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As detailed under &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion2/software/&#34;&gt;the section on criterion 2&lt;/a&gt;, I have spent a considerable amount of time and
effort building educational web applications used on the statistics courses
at Winona State. Before I could create these applications, I need to learn
how to write a client-side application similar to those provided by
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lock5stat.com/StatKey/&#34;&gt;StatKey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary obstacle to learning to create such an application is learning
JavaScript, which I haven&#39;t had the motivation to learn. I prefer to dedicate
myself to learning programming languages that differ from the languages I
have already mastered, but JavaScript is pretty similar to Python. Also, I
look for languages that are easy to use right out of the box, with tools for
building, installing, and running an application without a lot of
configuration. Elm fits all of these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn to create applications in Elm, I started my course of self-study by
completing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://guide.elm-lang.org&#34;&gt;standard Elm tutorials&lt;/a&gt;, but the
best way to learn a programming language is to build something. I spent a
significant part of the 2018 summer break creating the exact binomial
application (discussed in more detail in the section on &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion2/software/&#34;&gt;criterion 2&lt;/a&gt;)). It is a testament to the simplicity of the
Elm language that I could go from knowing nothing to build a complete
application in one summer. Since then, I have continued to gain mastery in
Elm by, for example, learning to add animations to the binomial simulation
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-in-preparation-for-two-new-dsci-courses&#34;&gt;Study in Preparation for Two New DSCI Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second course of self-guided study was conducted in preparation in
preparation for DSCI 330 and DSCI 430, two new electives that were developed
for the data science program. Each course required my to master new topics
and software tools as discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mastering-two-and-a-half-new-python-platforms&#34;&gt;Mastering Two (and a Half New) Python Platforms**&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the creation of materials for DSCI 430, I needed to learn three Python
platforms used to manage structured data: dfply, a module for processing
table using pipes and data verbs; sqlalchemy, a Python library for working
with SQL databases using an object-relational model (ORM); and PySpark SQL,
which allows the management of structured data that is distributed over any
many machines. Furthermore, I also mastered a third&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act of working through problems in all three frameworks has also
reaffirmed that this is all of the same stuff, and a realization that
has had a profound effect on my teaching in all data science courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;learning-to-process-audio-and-image-data&#34;&gt;Learning to Process Audio and Image Data**&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As suggested by the name, DSCI 330 The Management of Unstructured Data
focuses on the management of various forms of data that do not fit neatly in
tables. While I already has experience with two common examples of
unstructured data, text and web data, I did not have experience working with
audio, images, and video. Consequently, preparation for the course started
with becoming familiar with the theory and methods used when managing these
data formats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, while developing material about the spectrogram of an audio
signal, I studied about the theoretical foundations of the Fourier and
inverse Fourier transformations and pedagogical approaches to giving students
an understanding of these transformations. I now have a better understanding
of several other topics, including the application of various filters to
audio and images, using filters to search for a feature in an image, and
feature extraction for audio classification.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending Professional Meetings and Conferences</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/meetings_and_conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/meetings_and_conferences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the formal online coursework and self-guided study highlighted
in the previous section, I also attended five national conferences
dedicated to the practice and/or teaching of data science. Here is a list of conferences that I attended over the last 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://us.pycon.org/2017/&#34;&gt;PyCon 2017, Portland OR, May 17-25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://icots.info/10/?abouticots&#34;&gt;10th International Conference on Teaching Statistics (ICOTS), Kyoto, Japan, July 8-13, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberal Arts Data Science Workshop 2018 (LADS), New College of Florida, Sarasota FL, Jan 12-13, 2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/sdss/2019/&#34;&gt;2019 Symposium on Data Science and Statistics (SDSS 2019), Belleview, WA, May 29-Jun 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/sdss/2020/&#34;&gt;2020 Symposium on Data Science and Statistics (SDSS 2020), Virtual Conference, June 3-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
