<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | Tenure and Promotion Portfolio</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I present this online portfolio in support of my application for tenure and
promotion to the rank of Associate Professor in the Department of Mathematics
and Statistic. This portfolio will differ from most, in that I came to Winona
State as an experienced teacher. I have accumulated nearly 20 years of
teaching experience and was been granted tenure and promoted to Associate
Professor and Chair of the Department of Mathematics, Computer Science, and
Statistics at Saint Mary&#39;s University of Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&#39;t easy leaving a tenured position to start over at a new school, but
the opportunity to join the statistics and data science faculty at Winona
State was too good to pass up. Over the last four and a half years, I have
been able to complement and improve the data science program at Winona State
using my training as a statistician, previous research in machine learning,
and experience teaching programming. I also will provide evidence of
sustained growth and excellence in all the other activities&amp;ndash;quality
instruction, service, scholarship, continuing education, and a dedication to
student growth&amp;ndash;need to succeed as a faculty member at a 4-year liberal arts
university.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
