<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching Effectiveness | Tenure and Promotion Portfolio</title>
    <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/</link>
      <atom:link href="yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Teaching Effectiveness</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/yardsale8.github.io/tenure/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Teaching Effectiveness</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Design</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/curriculum_design/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/curriculum_design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When first joining the faculty as Winona State, I was very excited to learn
about and contribute to the curriculum of the data science program. Over the
course of the last four years, I have had a substantial impact on this
curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/testimonial/hooks_letter_of_support.pdf&#34;&gt;letter of support&lt;/a&gt;,
Dr. Hooks stressed these contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our data science program has significantly improved since Todd joined our
faculty. He created two new courses on his own to fill gaping holes in the
curriculum, which is a daunting and time-demanding task. Furthermore, he also
worked with other faculty members to improve existing data science courses.
His expertise is valued by us all, and we often seek out his advice. Todd is
always willing to offer ideas and opinions to his colleagues - even for
courses he is not currently teaching - no matter how busy he is with his own
teaching assignment. He is committed to making our courses better, regardless
of whether he is the one teaching them or not, and his efforts have had a
positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the contributions he has made to our data
science program alone along with the work he’s done to share his ideas with
the larger data science/statistics community are enough to warrant tenure and
promotion, but Todd has gone above and beyond to also improve our statistics program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As eluded to in Dr. Hook&#39;s comments, I have also made contributions to the
statistics curriculum, evidenced by the learning applications discussed in
one of the sections for &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion2/software/&#34;&gt;criterion 2&lt;/a&gt;,
the STAT 310 project discussed in the section on &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/instructional_innovation/&#34;&gt;instructional
innovation&lt;/a&gt;, and my work
aligning the curriculum of STAT 110 and STAT 210 discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In informal conversations, Dr. Chris Malone has indicated that he hoped that
adding me to the faculty would lead to improvements in
the data science curriculum in general and students&amp;rsquo; programming skills in particular. By the
end of this section, you will have seen evidence of my contributions in both
of these areas; as well as examples of my contributions made to the
statistic program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;curriculum-development-for-data-science&#34;&gt;Curriculum Development for Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I will discuss my primary contributions to the data science
curriculum, which comes in the form of two new courses and a revamped
curriculum for the introductory data science course. In the following
sections, I will discuss the creation of DSCI 330 and DSCI 430, give an
overview of the revamped DSCI 210 curriculum, and finally discussing my
efforts to improve students&amp;rsquo; programming skills throughout these three
courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dsci-330--the-management-of-unstructured-data&#34;&gt;DSCI 330 – The Management of Unstructured Data&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/330_project.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. Benjamin and Tyler teach the class about background subtraction using Python and the OpenCV library.  The final project in DSCI 330 requires groups of students to explore and present on a new topic in image and video processing.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/330_project.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; Benjamin and Tyler teach the class about background subtraction using Python and the OpenCV library.  The final project in DSCI 330 requires groups of students to explore and present on a new topic in image and video processing.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Description.&lt;/strong&gt; This course will give students an overview of the
issues related to the management of unstructured data, that is any data that
is not stored in a table or database. Sources of unstructured data include
bodies of text, social media applications, images, and audio. In the process
of exploring various forms of unstructured data, students will be exposed to
new programming languages and tools that are useful for managing this type of
data (e.g. Python and bash). Other topics covered in the course include web
scraping, natural language processing, and manipulating images/videos/audio
files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; This course fills a void in the previous curriculum.
It is estimated that between 50% and 80% of new data is unstructured (see
&lt;a href=&#34;http://breakthroughanalysis.com/2008/08/01/unstructured-data-and-the-80-percent-rule/&#34;&gt;Unstructured Data and the 80%
Rule&lt;/a&gt;.
Current and future data scientists will rely on the skills needed to gain
insight from these data sources. Before adding these courses, the program had
several offerings that provided students with experience working with
structured data, but there was little exposure to unstructured data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is designed to expose students to the methods and techniques
necessary to work with unstructured data. Students in the course learn to
process various types of unstructured data: text, data from the web,
audio, images, and video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague Dr. Silas Bergen sat in on DSCI 330 this fall and had
the following comments in his &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/testimonial/bergen_letter_of_support.pdf&#34;&gt;letter of
support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Iverson has also developed two entirely new, upper-level courses to our
curriculum (DSCI 330: Management of Unstructured Data and DSCI 430: Data at
Scale). I was able to sit in on DSCI 330 last semester and learned a lot
about the challenges students will face with messy data in the workplace and
the Python coding tools they can use to tackle those challenges. These are
both very strong courses and stellar additions to our Data Science
curriculum. Suffice to say, Dr. Iverson has been a boon for our Data Science
program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the material for the course can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wsu-DSCI330&#34;&gt;the DSCI 330 GitHub
organization&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dsci-430--data-science-at-scale&#34;&gt;DSCI 430 – Data Science at Scale&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/lew_presents.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. Daniel demonstrates a dashboard created as part of his capstone project illustrating what he learned in about processing data in Python and PySpark in DSCI 430.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/lew_presents.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; Daniel demonstrates a dashboard created as part of his capstone project illustrating what he learned in about processing data in Python and PySpark in DSCI 430.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Description.&lt;/strong&gt; The focus of this course is on exposing students to
processing data on a large scale using a distributed platform. First,
students will learn the functional approach to processing large data sets.
Along the way, we will encounter many of the techniques that are employed in
large distributed data-processing systems, such as using common higher-order
functions, employing lazy evaluation, and relying on immutable data
structures. By the end of the course students will be familiar with
processing large amounts of data in one or more high-level languages (e.g.
Python and/or Scala) and working with several frameworks for distributed
computation (e.g. Hadoop/MapReduce/Spark).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; This course filled a second void in the previous DSCI curriculum,
which lacked coverage of working with data on a large scale, that is data
that is too large to process on a single machine. This is a problem
with most data science programs, which become apparent when judging data
analytics competitions such as MUDAC and MinneMUDAC. I aimed to correct
this problem with this course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students in this course are introduced to working with data at three
different scales. First, they learn to process data relatively small data
(i.e. fits in RAM) using the standard Python tools of Pandas and the dfply
libraries. Next, students work with data that is too large to hold in RAM, but
can be processed on a single machine using a SQL database. Finally, students
work with PySpark, which can work with massive amounts of
data, data so large it must be distributed across the hard drives of many
machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of working with these three different platforms, we reinforce
an idea that was first introduced in DSCI 210, that is &amp;ldquo;it&#39;s all the
same stuff&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;that data management is translating the same general processes
to different platforms. While I am in the processes of updating the material for
this semesters class, the materials from the 2019 course can be found on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yardsale8/DSCI430&#34;&gt;DSCI 430 GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;teaching-students-to-write-better-code&#34;&gt;Teaching Students to Write Better Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secondary aim of these courses was to introduce students to a new
programming language and improve their programming skills. Strong programming
skills are a requirement for data scientists. Trends in data science tend to
move quickly and future data scientists must be exposed to many programming
languages and develop the ability to learn new languages or platforms.
Furthermore, developing the ability to write clean, correct, and
well-documented code will make students more efficient and valuable members
of a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To meet these aims, course material in DSCI 330 and DSCI 430 is supplemented
with lectures on writing better code, including selecting good names, writing
unit tests and proper documentation, and refactoring to clean up code. Also,
students are introduced to the data science modern toolset, including
technologies such as git, GitHub, Jupyter notebooks, and Docker.  I am pleased
to say that I have had multiple students thank me for helping them become
better programmers. For example, here is an email I received from Shane Will,
who graduated with a double major in computer science and data science,
shortly after taking my course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good Evening Dr. Iverson,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to thank you for pushing me in the Python course this past
spring. I have realized that my programming skills have really improved after
being pushed to write in a functional style. I know that if it was not for
that class and your pushing me I would not have improved my development
style. Thanks again and I hope that your summer has been going well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shane Will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another recent data science graduate, Mariah Quam, in her &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/testimonial/quam_letter_of_support.pdf&#34;&gt;letter of
support&lt;/a&gt; for this proposal, had to
say after taking three of my programming course (including DSCI 330 and 430).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are specifically three coding classes I took with Professor Iverson
that allowed me to accrue exponential growth in my coding ability. Through
these classes, he showed his ability to make what should have been boring and
tough lecture topics into engaging and thought provoking class periods by
using his great sense of humor and interactive approaches. On top of being a
great professor in the classroom, he shined through his office hours just as
much as he did in the classroom. I commend him for the amount of patience I
have witnessed him to have first hand with me and also with other students.
One thing I love about Professor Iverson is he truly cares about his
students&amp;rsquo; learning. He is not one to just give a student the answer to get
them out of his face or to leave them high and dry with no help. He is the
definition of going the extra mile when it comes to teaching students the
process of coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it should be noted that I presented some of these ideas at SDSS
2019, which is discussed &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion2/presentations/&#34;&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implementation-of-a-project-based-and-concept-driven-curriculum-for-dsci-210&#34;&gt;Implementation of a Project-Based and Concept-Driven Curriculum for DSCI 210&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing the two new DSCI courses, as well as advising and judging with
students in data analytics competitions, had the added benefit of clarifying
what data science is all about and formalizing a set of beliefs in how it
should be taught. A summary of these beliefs follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software-agnostic data management.&lt;/strong&gt; Many books and courses on data science focus
on teaching specific technologies or platforms, but we focus on giving students
a general abstract vocabulary for solving data management and visualization
tasks, then translating this language to specific technologies. DSCI 210 now
incorporates this approach by teaching data management verbs, then
translating these verbs to JMP, OpenRefine, and R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honoring the 80%.&lt;/strong&gt; It is often noted that a data scientist will
spend 80% of their time managing data and only 20% of their time later
analyzing the data. While many courses devote much of their time to teaching
the tools for the final analyses, we believe that data curriculum should
&lt;em&gt;honor the 80%&lt;/em&gt;, that is provide substantial and focused training that
prepares them for this 80% of their work life. While DSCI 210 still provides
an introduction to data visualization and statistical learning, a majority of
the curriculum is devoted to data management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project-based learning.&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, we believe students learning is
*reinforced by tackling complicated problems. To facilitate this learning,
*DSCI 210 now includes multiple projects that allow students to apply what
*they have learned to real-world problems, as well as practice presenting
*their findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last two years, I had the opportunity to incorporate these into a
revamped curriculum for DSCI 210, the introductory course in data
science.  After polishing the new curriculum over two semesters, I handed the course off to my colleague Dr. Silas Bergen, who had this to say about the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will specifically speak to my own personal experience teaching DSCI 210,
our introductory Data Science course, for the first time in Fall 2019. When
we first offered this course prior to Dr. Iverson’s arrival at Winona State,
we were very much “feeling around in the dark” with the course. Data Science
was a very new field in general, and there was little in the way of
established curriculum upon which to base the course. However, by the time I
taught the course, after Dr. Iverson had taught it several times, it had
developed into a very impressive course. Its conceptual flow was strong and
the assignments were high-quality, effectively reinforcing class concepts.
Dr. Iverson had discovered an important data cleaning tool, OpenRefine, and
introduced it to the course. Students glommed onto this tool and used it in
subsequent data analytics competitions. OpenRefine is now a mainstay of the
course. But Dr. Iverson’s most important contributions to this course, and to
the Data Science curriculum as a whole, is a “software agnostic” philosophy.
“Data Science” is not the learning of tools, or a pedagogy centered around
e.g. “learning how to code in Python” (though these tools are definitely
important). Rather Dr. Iverson has helped us as a department realize that
Data Science has theoretical and conceptual foundations that transcend any
one tool, and advocated for a curricular approach that exposes students to a
variety of tools with the idea that they should use the right tool for the
job. This has greatly strengthened our program and this philosophy touches
all aspects of our curriculum, from management of structured data to data
visualization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last semester, I had the opportunity to teach DSCI 210 again; this time
taking advantage of the excellent additions added by Dr. Bergen. The course
is finally in an excellent place, as evidenced by the following student
evaluation comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I really enjoyed this class and ending up adding Data Science to be my second major. I thought you did a wonderful job teaching and I feel like I learned so many useful tools to apply to my other studies in this class. Thank you so much!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;This course made me consider getting a major in DSCI. I HIGHLY HIGHLY recommend this course to other students.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;curriculum-development-for-statistics&#34;&gt;Curriculum Development for Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to highlight some of the curricula I developed for the
statistics program. In addition to the project I developed for STAT 310 in the
section on &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/instructional_innovation/&#34;&gt;instructional innovation&lt;/a&gt;, I also spent some time
aligning the curriculum between my STAT 110 and STAT 210 courses, in an
attempt to better understand issues with substituting one course for another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;creating-a-bridge-between-stat-110-and-stat-210-curriculum&#34;&gt;Creating a Bridge Between STAT 110 and STAT 210 Curriculum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am always looking for efficiencies in the implementation of the many class
preparations. One semester, I had two sections of STAT 210 on the same day as a
STAT 110 section and I determined that these courses could be designed to
share about 80% of the same content, meaning that for 80% of these courses
could be considered a single preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the semester, I mapped out the semester for both courses, lining up
the material on as many days as possible. Then adjustments were made to keep
the courses on the same schedule while finding room for the additional
material in STAT 210. This alignment was accomplished through additional
out-of-class activities in STAT 210 using presented through online videos
and/or adding additional practice activities for STAT 110.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written assessments were constructed in the same vein. Each written
assignment shared 4 questions, while the STAT 210 assignments had a
5th question that covered the additional material not covered in STAT
110. Both courses used the same set of practice and regular quizzes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach was a success in two ways. First, I (almost) made it through
that semester with my sanity in tack, but I realized that there is another
advantage to going through the process of aligning these courses. Frequently,
students that have taken STAT 110 will change to a major or minor that
requires STAT 210. In the past, the statistic faculty had a process for
converting a STAT 110 to STAT 210 (a test), but that approach is lost to
time. The following semester, I piloted using the supplementary material
developed for STAT 210 as a “course packet” that completed by one of my
former STAT 110 students that need STAT 210 after a change of major. In the
end, the statistic subgroup decided on an alternative route, I am grateful
for the chance to gain a better understanding of the relationship between
these courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section, you have seen evidence of substantial and meaningful
contributions to the curriculum of both the data science and statistics
programs, as well as evidence of my efforts to improve the coding skills of
students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructional Innovation</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/instructional_innovation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/instructional_innovation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of my STAT 110 Fundamentals of Statistics curriculum good
illustration of my approach to blending instructional innovation and the
assessment of student learning. STAT 110 is ripe for a discussion of
instructional innovation tied to the assessment of student learning due to
the demand and large sections (37 versus 25), which has translated
into an opportunity to teach the course in multiple formats, be it
face-to-face in the classroom, online asynchronously over the summer, or in
an online synchronous format due to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section, I will provide an overview of how the course material has
evolved from a face-to-face flipped classroom for STAT 110 and then
translating this material to synchronous and asynchronous online courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The face-to-face rendition of this course is built around the flipped
classroom, which is discussed in more depth in the section on &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/student_centered/&#34;&gt;criterion
4&lt;/a&gt;, but I would like to highlight a few
of the related innovations here. First, I embedded self-assessment
multiple-choice questions in an online and interactive set of course notes,
allowing students to check their understanding and review the material
outside of class. Next, the transition from a face-to-face flipped class to
an online format is discussed. Finally, I will discuss innovations that
evolved out of trying to develop authentic assessments that can be translated to
multiple formats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-embedded-self-assessments&#34;&gt;Using Embedded Self-Assessments&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/book_MC.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. An example of an embedded self-assessment. Students receive immediate feedback after reading each section of the book, including guidance for incorrect responses.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/book_MC.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; An example of an embedded self-assessment. Students receive immediate feedback after reading each section of the book, including guidance for incorrect responses.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two of my previous courses, STAT 110 and STAT 489, I constructed online
textbooks to supplement instruction. One of the primary advantages of
creating a web-based textbook is the ability to embed videos and
multiple-choice problems directly in the text. The students are asked to use
these assessments to gauge their understanding of the material, providing
immediate feedback and allowing them to determine if they have understood the
relevant material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These assessments are then used to prepare students for the end-of-module
assessments. Before wrapping up each module with a suite of larger
assessments, students are given a short quiz that consists of a random
selection of these book problems in hopes of encouraging them to go back and
review the associated material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of student evaluations, students were prompted to comment on the online textbook. Here are some positive responses related to the embedded assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;very useful. I liked the little multiple choice questions in the reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked this as well, with the check me quizzes and videos. Great resource for learning and exams&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The online textbook was useful to help in giving course examples, and the questions aligned with the reading quizzes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it useful in the way that practice questions were in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it useful especially the multiple choice questions embedded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the text book was very useful and i loved how they had multiple choice practice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the textbook extremely useful and liked the practice quizes/questions and videos. They helped me check my comprehension and also explained why I was wrong for some questions. a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I will discuss the translation of the flipped classroom into an online format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-implementation-of-and-online-stat-110&#34;&gt;The Implementation of and Online STAT 110&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/welcome.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2. Students are welcomed to the first week of STAT 110, an asynchronous online course taught during each of the 2017-2020 summer terms.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/welcome.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; Students are welcomed to the first week of STAT 110, an asynchronous online course taught during each of the 2017-2020 summer terms.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 2017 summer term, I had the opportunity to implement the first
online STAT 110 offering here at WSU. Since that time, STAT 110 has been
offered over multiple sections each summer term with an increasing demand
evidenced by the growing number of sections each year. There were several
challenges to adapting my materials to the online setting, which I will
summarize below. It should be noted that, in each case, the changes made in
anticipation of teaching online also greatly benefit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizational Challenges.&lt;/strong&gt; As discussed in the section on &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion3/continuing_education/&#34;&gt;criterion 3&lt;/a&gt;, first took the WeTeach courses in
the spring of 2017 and then revisited (and finally completed) the course in
the summer of 2020. This curriculum has shaped my approach to this online
course, and in particular, has taught me the importance of organization
and focused communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our summer offers are taught over eight weeks, which allowed for an easy
2-regular-weeks to 1-summer-week conversion and making it easy to map my
regular in-class activities to an online environment. The demands for better
organization forced me to rearrange the material into 8 modules, with one
module covered each week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make navigating the various components of the course easier, I
instituted a common numbering scheme for the whole course. First,
everything is numbered according to the encompassing module. Second, the
numbers for the readings were aligned with the corresponding activity.
For example, students should work through Section 5.1 in the book;
watching videos, reading the text, and attempting the self-assessment
problems; before attempting Activity 5.1. Then they move on to Section
5.2 and Activity 5.2, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Translating in-class group activities.&lt;/strong&gt; Another challenge was adapting my
classroom learning activities, which are usually completed in groups, to an
online setting. The asynchronous nature of the course precluded asking the
students to work in groups, so I decided that I would do my best to mimic
this classroom experience with recorded videos. For each activity, I led
students through an example, occasionally providing small lecture components,
and then asked students to pause the video and complete additional exercises
on their own. When they restart the video, I would go over my solution and
discuss common mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final challenge was implementing a robust online assessment scheme that
would give a meaningful and authentic assessment of student performance. It has
taking me years to implement a complete solution, which is discussed in the
next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;taking-advantage-of-randomized-practice-and-end-of-module-quizzes&#34;&gt;Taking advantage of randomized practice and end-of-module quizzes&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/quiz_scheme.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3. After adapting my assessments to an online setting, the final scheme involves material divided into three areas with corresponding review and practice materials.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/quiz_scheme.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; After adapting my assessments to an online setting, the final scheme involves material divided into three areas with corresponding review and practice materials.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When adapting my assessment materials to the online setting, I had three
motivating goals. First, I wanted to provide students with enough review and
practice to allow success while working on their own without support from
their peers. Second, I wanted to develop a scheme that took advantage of the
D2L features and allow for the quick turn around on feedback. Finally, I wanted
to fight academic dishonesty and get an authentic assessment of each
student&#39;s performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final implementation represents my best effort to balance and meet each
of these goals. The scheme consists of breaking assessment items into three
groups: knowledge-based assessments suitable to multiple-choice questions,
assessments of written interpretations, and checking computer skills. I will
discuss the reasoning for this split and the efficacy of my quiz scheme for
each of my original goals below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation.&lt;/strong&gt; The scheme for individual review through namely embedded
questions, writing review materials, and JMP how-to videos. Next students are
asked to practice what they have learned through practice quizzes and
worksheets. A key feature of the multiple-choice practice quiz is that
questions are pulled at random from a large bank of similar questions, which
allows students additional practice by repeating the quiz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prompt feedback.&lt;/strong&gt; By splitting the multiple-choice and written
quizzed questions into two separate quizzes allows for faster turn-around on
grading/feedback. D2L can automatically score the multiple-choice questions
these items and immediately provide students with their score, which wouldn&#39;t
be possible for quizzes that included short answer questions. I have also
found that I am more efficient in grading three short assessments consisting of
similar types of problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentic assessments.&lt;/strong&gt; After encountering issues with too much student
collaboration on homework assignments, I move as much material to D2L quizzes
as possible. Furthermore, multiple-choice and written assessments both pull
questions from a random bank of similar problems, making it harder for
students to collaborate on the quizzes (they likely get different questions
sorted in a different order). Finally, I made use of the Respondus Lockdown
Browser &amp;amp; Monitor, which locks down the student&#39;s computer and records their
activity using the web camera. Together these changes make it is much harder
for students to cheat on these assessments and much more likely that I get an
authentic assessment of student learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I will discuss a novel project I developed for STAT 310.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-virtual-pilot-study-for-stat-310&#34;&gt;A New Virtual Pilot Study for STAT 310&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently STAT 310 was changed to a writing-intensive course and last
year, Dr. Tisha Hooks and I developed a project to facilitate
written reports. In this project, students work in groups to design and
implement an experiment on &lt;a href=&#34;http://smp-island.smp.uq.edu.au/index.php&#34;&gt;The
Islands&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt;),
a virtual environment that provides a (fairly) authentic experience
working with human subjects. Students are required to gain a resident’s
consent before working with them and residents tend to drop
out of the study. Students are forced to think about realistic
expectations for measurable change over a short period, i.e. can
we expect a person’s IQ to change over a short period.
Finally, as in real life, obtaining a simple random sample is nearly
impossible and students are forced to design a reasonable (but flawed)
sampling scheme.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/islands.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3. The Islands is a virtual environment that allows students to conduct virtual experiments and studies. The three islands contain residents who can be found in their residence. After gaining consent, students can assign each resident a task as part of a larger study.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/islands.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; The Islands is a virtual environment that allows students to conduct virtual experiments and studies. The three islands contain residents who can be found in their residence. After gaining consent, students can assign each resident a task as part of a larger study.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first run of the project was promising, one problem that both
Dr. Hooks and I observed was most experiments resulted in
non-significant results. Power is one of the main topics early covered
in STAT 310 and is directly related to this problem: the first round of
studies either was looking for differences too minute to detect or
didn’t have enough participants to detect a difference that was present.
When performing expensive real-world studies, it is customary to first
perform a small pilot study that has several advantages. First,
conducting the pilot study allows the researcher to determine the
feasibility of the design and find any unforeseen problems. Second—and
more importantly—the researcher uses the resulting data to estimate the
sample size needed to have a good chance of finding a significant
difference, i.e. the sample size needed for a specified power level.
This important step makes sure that a researcher doesn’t waste their
time and money on an impossible task or waste too much time and money on
unneeded replications on an easy question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project provides the perfect opportunity to introduce students to
pilot studies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When redesigning this project, I started by reviewing the literature on
pilot studies, and found two very good articles to share with students.
In particular, Thabane et al. provide several resources,
including a detailed outline for reporting on a pilot study as seen in
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the revised version of the projects, students still started by
working in a group to propose a study. After getting some feedback from
the instructor, each group was required to conduct a pilot study and
write up their results using the outline provided by Thabane et al. . In
particular, each group was required to perform and report on the power
analysis for their research question. Then all of the students in the
class ranked the proposals with the top 3 proposals receiving a bonus.
Students were instructed to pay particular attention to the power
analysis and the amount of work estimated for each prospective study.
Then the whole class conducted a larger study based on the winning
design, with the winning team in charge of managing the class’s work.
Finally, each student wrote a final report on the class’s results.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/pilot_study.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 4. Thabane et al. provide, among other things, a detailed outline for a pilot study; which I found a useful guide for student reports.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/pilot_study.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.&lt;/strong&gt; Thabane et al. provide, among other things, a detailed outline for a pilot study; which I found a useful guide for student reports.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very pleased with the results of this project. I believe that
working with the Islands is a valuable and fun exercise, evidenced by
the student enthusiasm Dr. Hooks and I witnessed. Furthermore, I hope
that running the pilot study first gave the students real experience
with thinking about design feasibility and the importance of a power
analysis. Also, first writing about the pilot study and then writing about
the resulting main winning design offered the students a chance to see
two variations on reporting on a study; with each report tailored to the
goals of the respective design.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/example_project.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 5. The outcomes of one student project, where a randomized experiment was conducted to compare the effects of petting two types of animals to a baseline control.  As expected, petting a crocodile raises the average heart rate compared to the other two treatment groups.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/example_project.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5.&lt;/strong&gt; The outcomes of one student project, where a randomized experiment was conducted to compare the effects of petting two types of animals to a baseline control.  As expected, petting a crocodile raises the average heart rate compared to the other two treatment groups.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleague Dr. Tisha Hooks used this project in her subsequent STAT 310 courses, and her comments (taken from her &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/testimonial/hooks_letter_of_support.pdf/&#34;&gt;letter of support&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STAT 310 recently became a writing intensive course. Todd put a lot of work
into creating a writing project. Students were required to work in groups
to choose a research question of interest and then conduct a pilot study to
investigate that question in a virtual population known as The Islands. He
found articles that provide &amp;gt; students with the basic knowledge needed to
design a pilot study, created an assignment description and rubric, and found
a way to make the project even more fun by encouraging competition amongst
the students. Fortunately for me, he was willing to share his work so that
I could use the same assignment in my sections. Overall, the STAT 310
course is currently in a very good place, and once again, I have Todd to
thank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Student Evaluations</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/course_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/course_development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have placed a lot of value on feedback from student evaluations and I have
tried to illustrate how I use this feedback throughout the portfolio. For
example, in-depth evaluation of student feedback related to the flipped
classroom in &lt;a href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/student_centered/&#34;&gt;the section building student-centered curricula&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/STAT110_evals_instructor.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. Student responses to questions about the instructor from all regular sections of STAT 110 from Fall 2016 to Fall 2020 (excluding summer courses).  A large majority of the students agreed or strongly agreed that the instructor was available, cared, and enthusiastic; as well as providing clear explanations, effective teaching, and helpful answers.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/STAT110_evals_instructor.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; Student responses to questions about the instructor from all regular sections of STAT 110 from Fall 2016 to Fall 2020 (excluding summer courses).  A large majority of the students agreed or strongly agreed that the instructor was available, cared, and enthusiastic; as well as providing clear explanations, effective teaching, and helpful answers.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the other areas of my student evaluations to which I pay particular
attention. The first is the block of questions devoted to the instructor of
the course. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; shows the student responses from all spring and fall
STAT 110 sections from 2016-2020. As you can see, the majority of the students
were pleased with the instruction in the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am focusing on STAT 110 here (the course that I have taught the
most both in terms of sections and students), you will find similar responses
in the reports for most classes, which are provided in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;links-to-all-student-evaluations&#34;&gt;Links to All Student Evaluations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you will find links to the student evaluations for all&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of my
courses. A more thorough evaluation of these results will be providing
as part of my tenure and promotion applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DSCI 210&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/Vt9qjV&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/ORYhiI&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/YqTMNT&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/laFqaX&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DSCI 330&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/zjrG9z&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/3ZTaRi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DSCI 430&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/X8khDD&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 110&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/kjqpOj&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/pOogrF&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summer 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/Tt6iw5&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/iFKOmi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/iFKOmi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/HT0B1h&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summer 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/d0g8cx&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/I4uxyx&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/RiL8It&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summer 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/p29RDZ&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/nwAz90&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/qaYttZ&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summer 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/EEA7nA&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 210&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/BNbLoA&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 303&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/yaQlXz&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/N9KZjQ&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/ttJeRm&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 310&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/nUnrWa&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/yGE64m&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/lHeeiX&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 321&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/1VHAQL&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/vcQCOk&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 365&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/VGOtng&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAT 489&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ql.tc/lOqvUh&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except STAT/DSCI/MATH 395 from spring 2018, as this course was
team-taught with Dr. Chris Malone, who was the primary instructor. I
don’t have evaluations for this course. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Support Activities for Teaching and Learning</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/support_activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion1/support_activities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While important, there is more to teaching than instructional
innovation and designing an effective curriculum. David Moore argued that we
should treat &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stat.purdue.edu/~dsmoore/articles/Craft.pdf&#34;&gt;teaching as a
craft&lt;/a&gt;, and in this
section I will discuss three attempts at improving my craft through the
support activities related to teaching and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closed-caption-videos-for-stat-110&#34;&gt;Closed Caption Videos for STAT 110&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption1.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. Making a caption request on MediaSpace is fast and easy. Simply navigate to Caption &amp;amp; Enrich and click submit with the default settings.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption1.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; Making a caption request on MediaSpace is fast and easy. Simply navigate to Caption &amp;amp; Enrich and click submit with the default settings.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2019, I was informed that one of my STAT 110 students was
hearing impaired and required closed captioning on all video lectures. Making
this accommodation was no small task, as I run this course using the flipped
classroom; with a large number of short (or so I thought) lecture videos.
Luckily, MediaSpace offers a machine captioning service that guarantees 70%
accuracy. This service is available to anyone at no cost and a request can be
made by simply navigating to &lt;strong&gt;Caption &amp;amp; Enrich&lt;/strong&gt; and clicking &lt;strong&gt;Submit&lt;/strong&gt;
with the default settings (&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2. While machine captioning does a pretty good job of translation, it has trouble translating math and has no way of knowing that “jump” is JMP.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;. While machine captioning does a pretty good job of translation, it has trouble translating math and has no way of knowing that “jump” is JMP.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While machine captioning is a good place to start, it has trouble
translating technical terms (e.g. standard deviation) or JMP (the
software used in STAT 110—which is pronounced “jump”). &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; shows
some examples of mistakes in machine captioning of one of my recent
videos for STAT 321.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3. Navigating to Caption &amp;amp; Enrich and clicking the edit icon opens the Closed Caption Editor; which allows you to edit the original translation while watching your video.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; Navigating to Caption &amp;amp; Enrich and clicking the edit icon opens the Closed Caption Editor; which allows you to edit the original translation while watching your video.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reviewing the first few translations, I realized that corrections were
needed, which can be accomplished using another MediaSpace tool. Once a
machine translation has completed, navigating back to &lt;strong&gt;Caption &amp;amp; Enrich&lt;/strong&gt;
(Figure 1) will allow you to edit the translation by clicking the edit icon;
which opens the Closed Caption Editor (&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;). This tool allows you to
edit the original translation while watching the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is a fairly straight forward process, captioning all 85 videos
from STAT 110 was a Herculean task. Even though it was a TON of extra work, I
am glad that I had the experience as I learned several valuable lessons in
the process. First, captioning 20-minute videos made the need for short
videos crystal clear. There were times when faced with a particularly long
video, I found it easier to just make a new, short video. &lt;em&gt;What clearer
indication could there be that a video is too long?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides highlighting some poor speaking habits (“um”; starting sentences
with “so”) and a tendency to talk too fast; I also realized that habits
that I developed giving live lectures for 20 years do not necessarily
translate to videos. In particular, I found that I tend to
repeat myself when making important points. I don’t think this is a bad
habit when giving live lectures because we all lose focus and forget
parts of any lecture. What I am starting to believe is that this habit
is counterproductive in a video lecture, as the ability to watch the
video again removes the need for a repetitious speaker.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption4.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 4. There were 85 videos in total that were captioned during the fall, organized here by course module. In addition to learning about the process of efficient captioning of videos, the experience also taught me how to make more effective videos moving forward.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/caption4.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.&lt;/strong&gt; There were 85 videos in total that were captioned during the fall, organized here by course module. In addition to learning about the process of efficient captioning of videos, the experience also taught me how to make more effective videos moving forward.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of watching and captioning 85 of my lecture videos
(&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;) has made me much more mindful of the viewer&#39;s needs and much
more dedicated to producing short, quality clear videos. Replaying and
editing new videos in Camtasia has become mandatory and I have also
started to add machine captions to all new videos. Luckily, making a
conscious effort to slow down and avoid my bad verbal habits has led to
better initial translations and hopefully a better experience for the
learner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I will discuss my on-going efforts to keep a teaching journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-google-calendar-as-a-teaching-journal&#34;&gt;Using Google Calendar as a Teaching Journal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in earlier PDP/PDRs, I have been looking for a sustainable
method of keeping a teaching journal. In the past, I have tried a number
of approaches including keeping a journal in Apple Notes and using an
iOS journaling app. I wasn’t able to make a habit out of any of the
approaches.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/calendar.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1: Each class is given its own Google Calendar (left-hand side) and all-day events are used for each class session (right-hand side).&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/calendar.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Each class is given its own Google Calendar (left-hand side) and all-day events are used for each class session (right-hand side).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last two semesters, I have been using events in my Google
Calendar to keep a journal for each class. While I haven’t developed
the habit of completing these entries every day, I have been able to keep up
enough (say 2/3 of all class periods) to suggest this approach is
sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate my process, please note that I have created a Google
Calendar for each of my courses (Figure 1 – left-hand side). For each
class session, an all-day event is created for the session, where the
name of the event gives a hint at the material covered that day (Figure
1 – right-hand side). The actual journal for each class session is kept
in the notes section of each event. Minimally, these notes outline the
material covered that day; but generally, also include information about
how the session(s) went, improvements made between/after each session,
and suggestions for future improvements. See Figure 2 for two examples
of the journal entries.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/calendar_details.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;*Figure 2: A teaching journal is kept in the notes section of each class session event. Documentation includes an outline of the day’s topics, a record of how the class session went, and suggestions for future improvement.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/calendar_details.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    *&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2:&lt;/strong&gt; A teaching journal is kept in the notes section of each class session event. Documentation includes an outline of the day’s topics, a record of how the class session went, and suggestions for future improvement.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tracking-grading-progress&#34;&gt;Tracking Grading Progress&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in earlier PDRs, moving to a paperless approach to teaching
has had one unfortunate consequence: It is harder to track grading
progress. In the past, papers would pile up … anxiety would build … and
grading would occur. Now that everything is digital, I have lost the
physical reminder to keep on grading.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/grading_progress.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3: My current approach to tracking grading progress. All assignments that need grading are listed under their perspective class and items that are graded on completion are marked with a *. The section on the right-hand-side is used to track today’s progress (and includes the illusive Caught Up check box … I don’t want to talk about that!)&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/grading_progress.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3:&lt;/strong&gt; My current approach to tracking grading progress. All assignments that need grading are listed under their perspective class and items that are graded on completion are marked with a *. The section on the right-hand-side is used to track today’s progress (and includes the illusive Caught Up check box … I don’t want to talk about that!)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last fall, I implemented a persistent visual reminder of my grading
progress. On the whiteboard in my office, I keep a list of outstanding
items in need of grading. I generally assign two types of assignments,
regular items and items that are graded on completion. Items that are
graded on completion are differentiated by a * and grading one of these
“counts” for about 1/3 of a regular assignment. My goal is to grade 1-2
regular items a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this method has made it easier to track my progress, I
have yet to check the “Caught Up” box more than a couple of times a
semester. Frankly, this last year was a pretty busy year, due to the
development a new course each semester, and I look forward to seeing how
well this approach works during a regular year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
