<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Contributions to Student Growth and Development | Tenure and Promotion Portfolio</title>
    <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/</link>
      <atom:link href="yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Contributions to Student Growth and Development</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/yardsale8.github.io/tenure/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Contributions to Student Growth and Development</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing Student-Centered Curricula</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/student_centered/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/student_centered/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For me the joys of teaching are two-fold. First, I take a lot of pleasure in
continually improving the pedagogy, curriculum, and administration of my
various courses. Second, I treasure the opportunity to have a lasting impact
on my student&#39;s lives. Next, I will provide evidence of substantial
contributions to student growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-the-flipped-classroom-in-stat-110&#34;&gt;Using the Flipped Classroom in STAT 110&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/flipped_word_cloud.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. All sections of STAT 110 over the last five years have been implemented using the flipped classroom.  The word cloud highlights common words from students&amp;rsquo; comments on the flipped classroom.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/flipped_word_cloud.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; All sections of STAT 110 over the last five years have been implemented using the flipped classroom.  The word cloud highlights common words from students&amp;rsquo; comments on the flipped classroom.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in the fall semester of 2016, STAT 110 were implemented using the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flipped_classroom&#34;&gt;flipped classroom pedagogy&lt;/a&gt;,
with lectures were provided outside of class in the form of short videos embedded in an online
textbook and class time reserved for supplemental activities design to reinforce the material. students worked on homework in class.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/flipped_response.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2: STAT 110 students were asked to comment on the flipped classroom. The following table summarizes the responses with a large majority of the students giving a positive response.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/flipped_response.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;: STAT 110 students were asked to comment on the flipped classroom. The following table summarizes the responses with a large majority of the students giving a positive response.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research indicates that the flipped classroom can be effective. For example,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/26915403&#34;&gt;Zheng et al. (2020)&lt;/a&gt;
performed a meta-analysis on 95 studies that involved 15,386 participants and
found that the flipped classroom had a moderate effect on both learning
achievement and learning motivation. Additionally, they were able to show
that watching teaching videos before each class had the largest effect on
learning.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/act_and_videos.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3: STAT 110 students were asked to comment on the flipped classroom. The following table summarizes the responses with a large majority of the students giving a positive response.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/act_and_videos.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;: STAT 110 students were asked to comment on the flipped classroom. The following table summarizes the responses with a large majority of the students giving a positive response.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of these findings, I wanted to look at my students&amp;rsquo; opinions of this
approach. First, I looked at their response to the out-of-class videos and
in-class activities. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt; provided a summary of student responses to
two questions about both the out-of-class videos and in-class activities. In
all cases, a large majority of students either strongly agreed or agreed
that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The activities were enjoyable and beneficial and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The videos were understandable and that they watched them all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/sentiment_SVD.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 4: A latent sentiment analysis and singular value decomposition was performed on the student evaluation responses to Comment on the flipped classroom.  A summary and exemplar of typical responses in each region is provided.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/sentiment_SVD.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;: A latent sentiment analysis and singular value decomposition was performed on the student evaluation responses to &lt;em&gt;Comment on the flipped classroom&lt;/em&gt;.  A summary and exemplar of typical responses in each region is provided.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was interested in exploring the students&amp;rsquo; written responses when
prompted to respond to the flipped classroom. To help organize the responses
from hundreds of students across four-plus years of running the course, JMP
was used to perform a latent sentiment analysis and singular value
decomposition. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt; provides a summary of the findings, where we find
a cluster of very enthusiastic students in the top right, complaints about
the time and efficacy of videos in the bottom right, and short positive and
negative responses in the top and bottom left, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;To further illustrate the enthusiam of some of the student responses, I have
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;selected several additional comments from the top right quadrant, which are
provided below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LOVED. Gave us time to work on assignments and ask questions while we were doing the assignments [2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked being able to ask questions in class while doing the assignments [8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked this because then while in class, you could ask for help on the activities and ask questions about unclear things in the lectures. [9]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved this. It allowed me to take quality notes and if i wasn&#39;t quite understanding a concept I had the opportunity to go back and watch the video again. Coming to class and doing the activities was super beneficial. I liked being able to talk problems out with my peers and being able to ask you questions when needed. [17]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much better than the normal way. Gave me more time out of class and made for better grades on assignments. [33]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ii liked the style of the flipped classroom, but it would&#39;ve been nice to be also be able to work on homework outside of class, instead of in groups in class all of the time. [48]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked this approach and I think that it is a great way to teach students. I think that it allows them to ask questions in class if need be and it really breaks down the material. [55]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was helpful at times because I was able to ask hw questions in class, but the material is a little bit more difficult to memorize when its flipped classroom [79]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the flipped classroom becauseI liked being able to work through the work together and ask questions. [97]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it was good overall because most of the homework I definitely would not have been able to figure out on my own. I liked it even more when we started doing more in class activities rather than just group work. [107]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked the flipped classroom. It gave us a chance to do in class work and we were able to get help if we had questions. [110]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i did not mind it. As long as I read the book at home and looked through the powerpoints, I understood the material on the group work and the professor was able to answer any questions I had and clarified material during group work [119]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the flipped classroom approach because I was able to come to class with questions and get help on the homework in class. [120]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as i said before, I really liked it! gave me time to do hw in class and watching the videos on my own time and really getting to know it was nice! [123]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I most definitely preferred when the professor would talk and work on the assignments with us. I think I learned the material much better this way. [136]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked working on activities in class so that you can ask questions. [168]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked doing the activities in class because that way if you had questions, you could ask the professor right away. [174]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved the flipped classroom! I think that it gave students the best understanding for the class. I would rather learn in class and do my homework there than have to read textbooks [182]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if every class did that (and more and more are) students get bogged down with too many hours of watching lectures plus homework assignments plus studying and working. I like having the information available but it has a potential to increases the work load too high. [192]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked this approach! I think this really aligned with my style of learning and it helped a lot that class time you put what you learned to work with assignments while being able to work in groups. [237]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked it, for some modules I would have wanted a lecture however. But I think it made class time more useful. College is mostly peer collaboration anyways, so being able to contribute and better that skill through this class was super nice. All students are at a different pace, so he let us work on our own and if we were confused we knew where we could find him, he would answer the questions then and there rather than having to go to office hours. That was also nice. [251]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t like the flipped approach because I have become accustom to taking notes and learning in class and sometimes had a difficult time doing group activities when group members were also confused [256]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked it, because we already knew what we were going to do in class and it gave us time to ask you questions in class if needed. [260]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an interesting change as this is the first time I had done something like this. I believe that this approach with an incompetent professor can be potentially disasterous; however, Professor Iverson&#39;s setup with clear, online videos along with examples and help in the physical classroom made it work out very well. [267]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually liked being able to know what we were going to work on being able to have my peers and professor available when we got stuck on certain questions. [286]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes watched videos or read before class and group work everyday [287]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked this approach because I was able to read and watch the material before class and come to class with questions.  I also though working on the assignments with a group and asking questions as I did the assignments was helpful. [288]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked this approach cause it gave me more of an opportunity to ask questions about topics I was confused on. [290]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed it. Gave me a better understanding to watch before and then discuss material to help that understanding. [295]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t like the activities outside of class.  I didn&#39;t like how if we were confused we couldn&#39;t ask questions. [297]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great resource to understand the material on our own time and get help when needed in class [299]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not always read the textbook chapters assigned before class but other than that I liked the flipped approach. Working in groups and having the professor available for questions was extremely helpful [320]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer this approach for this stats class because it allows students to ask the professor questions while completing the work which otherwise could not be asked if the work was done at home. [332]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this helped me a lot because I was able to ask my homework questions in class [344]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I did not like it, but others might! I like learning over the material in a classroom setting and not by myself incase I have questions or am confused. [368]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flipped approach was good it was helpful you will have a better understanding of  the material. However, even if some did not I feel that your teaching is so thorough in class that, you wouldn&#39;t feel behind even if you didn&#39;t read or watch the videos. [379]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually enjoyes the flipped classroom approach, because I feel I learn better outside the classroom. It however leave more responsibility on myself and I would sometimes forget to do the assignments. [385]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the flipped approach was a great way to learn statistics. I enjoyed being able to ask questions during class. [387]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the flipped approach. It was very helpful to have time for homework in class so I could talk with my group members and Professor Iverson when I had questions. [392]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have never been apart of it before it was nice to be able to ask questions as we were working on the assignment in class. I did feel a little rushed doing the assignments in class [409]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoy this more than a typical classroom setting, working in class with people gave me the opportunity to ask questions and make friends. [415]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked it. Being able to use class time to ask questions was beneficial. [417]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t mind it because if i was confused on a part during the lecture, I would come to class and would be able to ask my group or the professor. [437]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It help because it gave me time to ask questions in class instead of outside of class [449]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked it, it gave us time to ask questions on assignments [456]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked it, the online vidoes were helpfull and it was nicin being able to ask questions in class when I needed help. [460]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, I am very pleased with the design and effectiveness of the
flipped classroom applied to STAT 110. I believe that this class, in
particular, is a good fit for this pedagogy; as it is home to a large number
of nursing majors who are very willing to put in the extra time. While I
don&#39;t have explicit proof demonstrating improved student learning, my
sense&amp;ndash;based off of years teaching this material with a standard approach&amp;ndash;is
that it also fosters better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, spending semester after semester in the flipped classroom has made
me a better instructor. It is hard to state how much I have learned, and
subsequently improved the course material, by directly observing the students
as they work together and ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-an-online-textbook-for-stat-110&#34;&gt;Building an Online Textbook for STAT 110&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/text_word_cloud.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 5:  This word cloud highlights common words from students&amp;rsquo; comments on the online textbook I put together for STAT 110.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/text_word_cloud.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt;:  This word cloud highlights common words from students&amp;rsquo; comments on the online textbook I put together for STAT 110.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my previous place of employment, I used an online textbook in an
introductory programming course which was developed by Brad Miller and David
Ranum from Luther College. This online textbook framework rethinks the role
of a textbook in the age of the internet by allowing authors to embed videos
and assessment questions in the body of the book. Furthermore, these authors have
released an open-source Python library that can be used to construct your own.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/book_MC.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 6:  An example of the multiple-choice assessments that are embedded in the online course textbook I designed for STAT 110.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/book_MC.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt;:  An example of the multiple-choice assessments that are embedded in the online course textbook I designed for STAT 110.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that this type of book would be a good match to the flipped
classroom approach to STAT 110. During the 2016-2017 academic year, I
converted Dr. Tisha Hooks&amp;rsquo; course notes into such an online textbook. In the
process, I made some adjustments to match the material to my preferences&amp;ndash;in
particular, introducing confidence intervals using on the StatKey
website&amp;ndash;and embedded short video lectures and multiple-choice The current
version of the book can be found using &lt;a href=&#34;https://yardsale8.github.io/stat110_book/&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of some of the book’s features. The book&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starts with an introduction to data and statistical studies,
including a focus on constructing sentences to describe parameters
and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uses the StatKey website and the bootstrap to introduce confidence
intervals for quantitative data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduces association for two quantitative variables and uses the
bootstrap to perform inference using the StatKey website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uses the Hooks/Malone approach of introducing hypothesis testing
through simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/book_comments.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 7:  A summary of responses from student evaluations for the Fall 2017 term of STAT 110. A majority of the students like the online textbook (right-hand plot), identifying cost, ease of access, embedded lecture videos and embedded assessments as positive elements (left-hand plot).&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/book_comments.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt;:  A summary of responses from student evaluations for the Fall 2017 term of STAT 110. A majority of the students like the online textbook (right-hand plot), identifying cost, ease of access, embedded lecture videos and embedded assessments as positive elements (left-hand plot).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each semester, students are asked to comment on the textbook.
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt; gives a summary of the results from the Fall 2017 semester. We
can see that a large majority liked the book (right-hand plot) and elements
that they found helpful (left-hand plot).  In particular, there was some
very strong feedback related to the embedded multiple-choice questions that
students could use for self-assessment. Here is an example of such a
response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Yes, I thought It was useful. I liked [t]he few questions you would
provide at the bottom of each section or video. I appreciated the
comments that went along with it, wheather [sic] I got the question
right or wrong, there was always a comment explaining why that was the
answer, which really helped me understand i[t] better. *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While putting together the online interactive textbook for STAT 110 was
time-consuming, it has paid enormous dividends over the last five years. In
particular, this approach has made moving to online teaching, both
asynchronously in the summers and synchronously in response to COVID-19, much
more manageable and I would encourage anyone to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assisting in the Scholarly Growth of Students</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One way to promote the scholarly growth of students is through
out-of-the-classroom activities that accentuate their in-class learning.
Next, I will highlight two such activities: my work advising students participating
in data analytics competitions and a workshop that I developed for the Women
in Computer Science (WiCS) student organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;advising-minnemudac-and-mudac-competitors&#34;&gt;Advising MinneMUDAC and MUDAC competitors&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/MinneMUDAC16.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. Winona State students presented their finds at MinneMUDAC 2016, with one team winning the Serendipitous Discovery award.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/MinneMUDAC16.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; Winona State students presented their finds at MinneMUDAC 2016, with one team winning the Serendipitous Discovery award.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in the 2016-2018 fall semesters, I have taken an active leadership
role in organizing and advising students competing in the MUDAC and
MinneMUDAC data analytics competitions. Participating in a data analytics
competition provides students an important opportunity to apply what they
have learned while working on a real-world problem with a team of peers.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/MinneMUDAC17.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 2. Five Winona State teams participated in MinneMUDAC 2017, winning the First Place Overall and Acumen awards.  Two other teams received an honorable mention.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/MinneMUDAC17.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; Five Winona State teams participated in MinneMUDAC 2017, winning the First Place Overall and Acumen awards.  Two other teams received an honorable mention.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of each competition, I collaborated with Dr. Chris Malone to
hold meetings with the participants in the weeks leading up to the main
event. We held these gatherings once or twice a week and used the time to
prepare the students for the competitions, particularly in two areas. First,
we reviewed the problem as well as techniques that the teams could use to
answer the corresponding questions. Second, we spent time reviewing strategies
for effectively presenting the student&#39;s findings.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/MUDAC18.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 3. Winona State teams participated in MUDAC 2018, a competition organized and administrated by WSU data science faculty, with one team  First Place Overall.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/MUDAC18.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; Winona State teams participated in MUDAC 2018, a competition organized and administrated by WSU data science faculty, with one team  First Place Overall.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These competitions have been a successful and meaningful experience for our
students and many of the WSU teams have performed well. For example, a WSU
team placed in the top five in the undergraduate division in the
MinneMUDAC 2016 competition and won the award for Serendipitous Discovery (see
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;). The following year saw even more success for WSU teams, with
two teams winning First Place Overall and the Acumen Award, respectively, and
another two teams receiving Honorable Mention in the MinneMUDAC 2017
competition (&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;). We saw similar success in the MUDAC 2018 competition with WSU
teams placing first, fourth, and eight in the overall competition (out of 36
teams) and our teams performed exceptionally well in the new prediction
accuracy portion of the competition, placing first, second, and sixth (&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I can&#39;t take full credit for the success of our teams, as we have very
hard-working and talented students, I would like to think that organizing and
administering the biweekly meetings before each competition contributed to not
only the success of our teams, but more importantly to students&amp;rsquo; growth as
statisticians and data scientists. I should also note that, in addition to
advising Winona State student teams and organizing study sessions, I also
helped organize and run the MUDAC 2016, MUDAC 2017, and MUDAC 2018
competitions hosted here at Winona State; those contributing the student
scholarly growth of students from neighboring schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wics-workshop-on-web-scraping&#34;&gt;WiCS Workshop on Web Scraping&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/WiCS_workshop.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Figure 1. I presented a workshop, organized by the Women in Computer Science student organization, on web scraping with Python.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;yardsale8.github.io/tenure/img/WiCS_workshop.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; I presented a workshop, organized by the Women in Computer Science student organization, on web scraping with Python.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This the spring semester of 2018, two former/current students asked me to
develop and present a workshop for the Women in Computer Science (WiCS)
students organization. The resulting workshop was based on the USCOTS
pre-conference workshop and introduced the students to scraping the web with
Python. The workshop ran for 2.5 hours and was attended by about 55 students.
While I don’t have formal feedback from the participants, informal comments
suggest that the workshop was a success.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising</title>
      <link>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/advising/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>yardsale8.github.io/tenure/criterion4/advising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The final set of activities promoting student growth and development I
will highlight are all related to advising. This is not limited to
academic advising, but also includes serving as an adviser for capstone
experiences&amp;ndash;be it research projects or internships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;academic-advising&#34;&gt;Academic Advising&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last four and a half years, I now have advised 34 students with data
science majors or minors. Students in our department are initially assigned
an advisor in their first year, and I have twice taken on all incoming majors
for that academic year. Students then have the option of selecting their
advisor moving forward. While some of my more experienced colleagues have
likely advised more students over the same period, I believe that I have
completed a decent share of the overall workload. Additionally, while I have
many years of experience advising students, I still needed to go through the
process of learning the systems and advising nuisances at Winona State. and
going through two rounds of advising this year has helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;supervising-of-student-based-research&#34;&gt;Supervising of Student-based Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, I had the opportunity to advise several students on
their capstone projects, each of which are summarized below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investigating Python Using Housing Data.&lt;/strong&gt; Catherine Nead was interested in
a capstone project that involved working with Python, developed a project
that involved using Python to automate the acquisition and processing of data
from Zillow through the use of an API. The resulting data were used to build
and test predictive models for predicting a home sale price using information
from comparable houses. This was a novel project in several ways. First,
the data was returned as JSON, which required Catherine to learn about this
data type and the associated Python toolset. Second, the data not only
included information on each house of interest, but also data on comparable
houses, which required careful feature selection and aggregation of the
information. Finally, Catherine had no prior experience with Python.
Catherine presented her work as a poster at the Ramaley Research Celebration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predicting Unemployment in Barcelona.&lt;/strong&gt; Jackie Sieve is a dual Spanish and
DSCI major and wanted to find a data science project related to her second
major. She studied unemployment in Barcelona during the 2008 recession by
building models to using several features to predict the unemployment numbers
for each neighborhood. Her resulting models did a fantastic job of predicting
unemployment, with the best models having an r-squared of around 99.7%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Verbs for SQL.&lt;/strong&gt; YingZhang (Daniel) Lew worked with me developing
Python tools that allow the application of data verbs to SQL databases in
Python. I went into more detail on these ideas in last year’s PDR. Daniel was
able to develop a large number of tools independently while learning about
important software engineering techniques and writing proper documentation,
continual development, and automated unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is too early to give details, I am currently supervising three more
student capstone research projects over this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;supervising-of-internships&#34;&gt;Supervising of Internships&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also served as faculty supervisor for seven previous or on-going
internships. While advising an internship isn&#39;t as involved as advising research
projects, it does require ensuring that the internship meets the needs of
STAT/DSCI 488, obtaining self and supervisor assessments of performance, and
translating those assessments into a final grade. Based on my experiences
with the first few internships, I have improved the student experience by
helping formalizes the application and requirements as well as developing
Qualtrics surveys used for self and supervisor performance evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
